<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A family well-ordered, or, An essay to render parents and children happy in one another handling two very important cases : I. What are the duties to be done by pious parents, for the promoting of piety in their children, II. What are the duties that must be paid by children to their parents, that they may obtain the blessings of the dutiful / by Cotton Mather.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50129</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16156254</idno>
  <idno type="VID">104904</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240860129</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W18658</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">16156254</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50129)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1597:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A family well-ordered, or, An essay to render parents and children happy in one another handling two very important cases : I. What are the duties to be done by pious parents, for the promoting of piety in their children, II. What are the duties that must be paid by children to their parents, that they may obtain the blessings of the dutiful / by Cotton Mather.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79, 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Green &amp; J. Allen, for Michael Perry ... &amp; Benjamin Eliot ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston [Mass.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An address, Ad fratres in eremo"--5 p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Family --  Religious life.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Parent and child.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104904:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104904:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Family Well-Ordered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR An ESSAY To Render Parents <hi>and</hi> Children Happy in one another. Handling Two very Important CASES.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>What are the Duties to be done by Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Parents, <hi>for the promoting of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in their</hi> Children.</item>
               <item>II. <hi>What are the Duties that must be paid by</hi> Children <hi>to their</hi> Parents, <hi>that they may obtain the</hi> Blessings <hi>of the Dutiful.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> COTTON MATHER.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mal. IV. 6.</hi>
               </bibl> He shall Turn the Heart of the Fathers to the Children, and the Heart of the Children to their Fathers.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Boston,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. Green,</hi> &amp; <hi>J. Allen,</hi> for <hi>Michael Perry,</hi> at his Shop over-against the Town-House: &amp; <hi>Benjamin Eliot,</hi> at his Shop under the West-End of the Town-House. 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:104904:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104904:2"/>
            <head>THE Duties of PARENTS To their Children.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. XVIII. 19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I know him, that he will command his Children and his Houshold after him, and they shall keep the way of the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS the Great God, who at the Beginning said, <hi>Let US make man after our Image,</hi> hath made man a <hi>Sociable</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, so it is evident, That <hi>Families</hi> are the <hi>Nurseries</hi> of all Societies; and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104904:3"/>First Combinations of mankind. <hi>Well-ordered Families</hi> naturally produce a <hi>Good Order</hi> in other <hi>Societies.</hi> When <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> are under an <hi>Ill Discipline,</hi> all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Societies</hi> being therefore <hi>Ill Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plined,</hi> will feel that Error in the <hi>First Concoction.</hi> To Serve the <hi>Families</hi> of our Neighbourhood, will be a Service to all our <hi>Interests.</hi> Every serious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian is concerned, That he may be <hi>Serviceable</hi> in the World; And many a serious Christian is concerned, because he sees himself to be furnished with no more <hi>Opportunities</hi> to be <hi>Serviceable.</hi> But art thou not a Member of some <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</hi> If that <hi>Family</hi> may by thy means, O Christian, become a <hi>Well-regulated Family,</hi> in that point thou wilt become <hi>Serviceable;</hi> I had almost said, <hi>Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensibly</hi> Serviceable. They that have the Government of some <hi>Family,</hi> do make up no Little part of this Great Assembly. And, Syrs, are there any of you, that would forfeit that Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Title, of all the Faithful, <hi>The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Abraham.</hi> Give your Attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ye <hi>Children of Abraham,</hi> while I set before you, the Example of your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> for your Imitation.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104904:3"/>
            <p>Our Glorious <hi>Lord-Messiah,</hi> is here going to Communicate unto <hi>Abraham</hi> some of His Heavenly Counsels. And we have a Text before us, that assigns a <hi>Reason</hi> for that gracious Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The <hi>Reason</hi> is, the care which this Good man, would thereupon take to bring up his <hi>Family</hi> in the Fear of God. In this Text there are some Remarkable Things; and things that some Wise men have often Remarked. There was an Excellent man, sometimes a Preacher of the Lord Jesus Christ, in this very place; whose custome it was, not only to Read a portion of the Scripture before his <hi>Prayers</hi> with his <hi>Family,</hi> but also to Infer and Apply brief <hi>Notes</hi> out of what he Read. He professed, That he found none of all his weary Studies in <hi>Divinity,</hi> so profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to him, as this one Exercise, for the Rare and Rich Thoughts, which he therein found himself supplied withal. And he Declared, <q rend="margQuotes">That he Looked on it, as an Accomplishment of this very word; <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham, the thing which I do? I know him, That he will command his Children, and his Houshold.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104904:4"/>
            <p>Moreover, You may here Observe a most comfortable Connexion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, <hi>He will,</hi> and, <hi>They shall.</hi> Saies the Lord, <hi>He will Command his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and They shall keep the way of the Lord.</hi> It seems, If every one that is Owner of a <hi>Family,</hi> would faithfully <hi>Command,</hi> and manage those that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto him, thro' the Blessing of God, they would generally <hi>Keep His Way,</hi> and His Law. I find a famous Writer in the Church, therefore thus expressing himself; <q rend="margQuotes">If <hi>Parents</hi> did <hi>their</hi> Duties as they ought, the <hi>Word</hi> publickly Preached, would not be the ordinary means of <hi>Regeneration</hi> in the Church, but only <hi>without</hi> the Church, among Infidels: God would so pour out His Grace upon the Children of His people, and Hear Prayers for them, and bless Endeavours for their Holy Education, that we should see the Promises made Good unto our Seed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>We will now Dismiss these Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and Repair to that <hi>Grand Case,</hi> which hence offers it self unto us.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104904:4"/>
               <head>CASE. <hi>What may be done by Pious Parents, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> of their <hi>Children?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>The <hi>Case</hi> Enquires, <hi>What may be done?</hi> You'l take it for granted, that the Answer to it, will tell you, <hi>What should be done?</hi> For you'l readily grant, that in such an Important <hi>Case</hi> as this, All that <hi>may</hi> be done, <hi>should</hi> be done.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Case,</hi> We Enquire after what is to be done, by <hi>Pious</hi> Parents. <hi>Other</hi> Parents will take no due Notice, of the Injunctions that God has Laid upon them concerning their <hi>Children. Parents,</hi> If you don't first become your selves <hi>Pious,</hi> you'l do nothing to purpose to make your <hi>Children</hi> so. Except you do your selves walk in the <hi>Way of the Lord,</hi> you will be very careless about bringing your <hi>Children</hi> to such a Walk. It is not a <hi>Cain,</hi> or a <hi>Cham,</hi> or any E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of God; that will do any thing to make his Children become the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of God. The Psalmist, in Psal. 34.1, 4, 11. could first say, <hi>I'l bless the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104904:5"/>Lord,</hi> and, <hi>I sought the Lord,</hi> and then he saies, <hi>Come ye Children, and I'l teach you the Fear of the Lord.</hi> O <hi>Parents,</hi> In the Name of God, Look after your own miserable <hi>Souls;</hi> How should those wretched people do any thing for the <hi>Souls</hi> of their <hi>Children,</hi> that never did any thing for <hi>their own?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>Case,</hi> we Enquire, after what is to be done by <hi>Parents</hi> for their <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> But let it be Remembred, That our <hi>Servants</hi> are in some sort likewise our <hi>Children.</hi> Our whole <hi>Houshold,</hi> as well as the <hi>Children</hi> that are our <hi>Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring,</hi> are to be taught the <hi>Way of the Lord.</hi> An <hi>Abraham</hi> will have his <hi>Train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Servants.</hi> We read concerning a certain Person of Quality, in 2 King. 5.13. <hi>His Servants came near and spake unto him, and said, My Father.</hi> Let not those of my Hearers, that are without such Invaluable Blessings of God, as <hi>Children,</hi> count themselves unconcerned in our Discourse, if they have any <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> under them. A considerable part of what is to be done for our <hi>Children,</hi> I pray, <hi>Masiers,</hi> Think, as we go along; <hi>Think,</hi> without our particular Inculcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether nothing. This may be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104904:5"/>done for your <hi>Servants:</hi> And, God make <hi>Eliezers</hi> of them for you!</p>
               <p>Attend now to the Counsils of God.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>I. Parents,</hi> Consider the <hi>Condition</hi> of your <hi>Children;</hi> and the Loud Cry of their <hi>Condition</hi> unto you, to Endeavour their <hi>Salvation!</hi> What an <hi>Army</hi> of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Thoughts, do at once now show themselves, to besiege your Hearts, and subdue them unto a just care for the <hi>Salvation</hi> of your Children!</p>
               <p>Know you not, That your <hi>Children</hi> have precious and Immortal <hi>Souls</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them? They are not all <hi>Flesh.</hi> You that are the <hi>Parents</hi> of their <hi>Flesh,</hi> must know, That your Children have <hi>Spirits</hi> also, whereof you are told, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. <hi>God is the Father of them;</hi> and in Eccles. 12.7. <hi>God is the Giver of them.</hi> The <hi>Souls</hi> of your <hi>Children,</hi> must sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive their <hi>Bodies,</hi> and are transcendent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Better and Higher &amp; Nobler Things than their <hi>Bodies.</hi> Are you sollicitous that their <hi>Bodies</hi> may be <hi>Fed?</hi> You should be more sollicitous that their <hi>Souls</hi> may not be <hi>Starved,</hi> or go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Bread of Life.</hi> Are you sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104904:6"/>that their <hi>Bodies</hi> may be <hi>Cloath'd:</hi> You should be more sollicitous, that their <hi>Souls</hi> may not be <hi>Naked,</hi> or go without the <hi>Garments of Righteousness.</hi> Are you Lothe to have their <hi>Bodies</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under <hi>Infirmities,</hi> or <hi>Deformities?</hi> You should be much more Loth to have their <hi>Souls pining away in their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</hi> Man, Are thy <hi>Children,</hi> but the <hi>Children of Swine?</hi> If thou art Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardless of their <hi>Souls,</hi> truly thou dost call them so! One of the Ancients, namely <hi>Cyprian,</hi> hath a pungent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison for this matter; <hi>Pray, Consider;</hi> (said that Great man,) <hi>He that minds his Childs Body more than his Soul, is like one, that if his Child and his Dog were like to be drowned, should be sollicitous to save his Dog, but let the Child perish in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> How <hi>deaf</hi> art thou, that thou dost not hear a loud cry from the <hi>Souls</hi> of thy Children in thine Ears, <hi>O my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my Mother, Look after me!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But more than so; Don't you know, That your <hi>Children,</hi> are the <hi>Children of Death,</hi> and the <hi>Children of Hell,</hi> and the <hi>Children of Wrath, by Nature:</hi> And that from <hi>you,</hi> this <hi>Nature</hi> is derived and conveyed unto them! You must know,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104904:6"/>
                  <hi>Parents,</hi> that your <hi>Children</hi> are by your means <hi>Born</hi> under the dreadful <hi>Wrath</hi> of God: And if they are not <hi>New-Born</hi> before they <hi>Dy,</hi> it had been <hi>Good for them, that</hi> they <hi>never had been Born at all.</hi> The law of acquity was, in Exod. 21.19. <hi>If one man wound another, he shall cause him to be throughly healed.</hi> Your <hi>Children</hi> are born with deadly <hi>wounds</hi> of Sin upon their Souls; and they may Thank <hi>you</hi> for those <hi>wounds:</hi> Unjust-men, will you now do nothing for their <hi>Healing?</hi> Man, thy Children are dying of an horrid <hi>poison,</hi> in their Bowels; and it was thou that <hi>poison'd</hi> 'em. What! wilt thou do nothing for their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccour! Thy Children are thrown into a Devouring <hi>Fire;</hi> and it is from thee that the <hi>Fiery</hi> Vengeance of God ha's taken Hold of them. What! wilt thou do nothing to Help them out! There is a <hi>Corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in thy Children, which is a <hi>Fountain</hi> of all Wickedness and Confusion. The very <hi>Pagans</hi> were not insensible of this <hi>Corrupt Nature;</hi> they Styl'd it our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genite Sin,</hi> and our <hi>Domestick Evil,</hi> and cry'd out, with <hi>Tully, Simul ac Editi su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in Lucem, ac suscepti, in omni continue pravitate versamur.</hi> The <hi>Jewes</hi> have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104904:7"/>been yet more Sensible of this <hi>Corrupt Nature;</hi> they have Stil'd it, our <hi>Evil Frame,</hi> and, The <hi>poison of the old Serpent;</hi> and <hi>This</hi> they understand by <hi>The Enemy,</hi> so osten mentioned in the Scripture; And, The <hi>Heart of stone,</hi> and, The <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that watches the Righteous.</hi> Will not <hi>you</hi> that are <hi>Christians,</hi> then show your <hi>Christianity,</hi> by Sensibly doing what you can, that your <hi>Children</hi> may have a <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Nature</hi> infused into them?</p>
               <p>What shall I Say? I may say, <hi>The Time would fail me to mention</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sandth part of what might be said. But, in short: Is it not a sad Thing to be <hi>The Father of a Fool?</hi> Alas, man, till thy <hi>Children</hi> become <hi>Regenerate,</hi> Thou art the <hi>Father of a Fool;</hi> Thy Children are but the <hi>Wild Asses Colt!</hi> I add; would it not Break thy Heart, if thy <hi>Children,</hi> were in Slavery to <hi>Turks,</hi> or <hi>Moors,</hi> or <hi>Indians? Devils</hi> are worse than <hi>Indians,</hi> and <hi>Infidels:</hi> Till thy <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> are brought home to God, they are the slaves of <hi>Divels.</hi> In a word; <hi>Can thy Heart Endure,</hi> that thy <hi>Children,</hi> should be Banished from the Lord Jesus Christ, and Languishing under the Torments of Sin among Devils, in outer Darkness
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104904:7"/>throughout Eternal Ages? Don't call thy self a <hi>Parent;</hi> Thou art an <hi>Ostrich?</hi> Call not these, the <hi>Children of thy Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els;</hi> Thou hast no <hi>Bowels!</hi> I will not say, That <hi>Zipporah</hi> call'd her <hi>Husband,</hi> A <hi>Bloody Husband.</hi> But all the Angels in Heaven call thee, A <hi>Bloody Father,</hi> and, A <hi>Bloody Mother;</hi> and are astonish'd at the Adamantine Hardness of that Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Heart of thine; and those Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strings that are Sinewes of Iron!</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Improve the <hi>Baptism</hi> of your <hi>Children,</hi> as an <hi>Obligation,</hi> and an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement</hi> unto you, <hi>Parents,</hi> to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the <hi>Salvation</hi> of your <hi>Baptised</hi> Little Ones. Of your <hi>Children,</hi> you may say, with <hi>Jacob,</hi> in Gen. 33.5. <hi>These are the Children, that God hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously given to me.</hi> Now, Will not you <hi>Heartily give back</hi> those <hi>Children</hi> to <hi>God</hi> again: Their <hi>Baptism</hi> is to be the <hi>Sign</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> of your doing so. You gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bring your <hi>Infant Children</hi> unto the <hi>Baptism</hi> of the Lord: I suppose, 'tis because you are satisfied, That the <hi>Children</hi> of Believers were in Covenans with God, in the Dayes of the <hi>Old Testament;</hi> and, That the <hi>Children</hi> of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104904:8"/>Then had a Right unto the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itial Seal</hi> of the Covenant; and, That in the Dayes of the <hi>New Testament,</hi> they have not Lost this priviledge. Well, But when you bring your <hi>Children</hi> to the Sacred <hi>Baptism,</hi> what is it for? Oh, Let it not be done, as an Empty <hi>Formality;</hi> as if the <hi>Baptism</hi> of your Children, were for nothing, but only a <hi>Formal</hi> and a <hi>Pompous</hi> putting of a Name upon them. No, but let the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Language of your Souls, in this Action, be that of <hi>Hannah,</hi> in 1 Sam. 1.28. <hi>I have given this Child unto the Lord, as long as he Lives he shall be given unto the Lord.</hi> I find in the private Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of an Holy Man, who dyed in this place, not much above a year ago; That the Day before one of his <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> was to be <hi>Baptised,</hi> he spent the Time in giving up himself and his Child unto the Lord, and in Taking hold of the <hi>Covenant</hi> for both of them, and in praying, that he might on the morrow, be able in much <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Covenant Obedience,</hi> to do it, at the <hi>Baptism</hi> of the Lord. On which he writes, <hi>It is not easie tho' common, to offer a Child unto God in Baptism.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104904:8"/>
               <p>Syrs, When you have done thus, for your <hi>Children,</hi> you have a singular Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to plead for the Fulfilment of that word upon them, in Isa. 44.3. <hi>I will pour my Spirit upon thy Seed, and my Blessing upon thy Offspring.</hi> You may go before the Lord, and plead, <hi>Lord, Was not the Baptismal Water poured by thy Command upon my Children! Oh, Do thou now pour upon them the Heavenly Grace, which that Baptismal Water Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> And now, no sooner let those <hi>Children</hi> become able to understand it, than you shall make them understand, what the Design of their <hi>Baptism</hi> was. <hi>Parents,</hi> I am to tell you, That if you Let your <hi>Children</hi> grow up, without e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver telling them, <hi>That,</hi> and, <hi>Why,</hi> they were <hi>Baptised</hi> into the <hi>Name</hi> of the Lord, you are fearfully Guilty of <hi>Taking the Name of the Lord in vain.</hi> It was the manner of an Excellent Minister, upon the <hi>Baptising</hi> of a <hi>Child,</hi> Solemnly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the <hi>Child</hi> into the Hands of the <hi>Parents,</hi> with such words as those, <hi>Here, Take This Child now, and bring it up for the Lord Jesus Christ, I charge you.</hi> God from Heaven speaks the like words to you, O <hi>Parents,</hi> upon all your <hi>Baptised
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104904:9"/>Children.</hi> And that you may <hi>bring up your Children for the Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> You must as soon as you can, Let them know, That in <hi>Baptism,</hi> they were <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated</hi> unto <hi>Him.</hi> Show them, That when they were <hi>Baptised,</hi> they were <hi>Listed</hi> among the <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, and that if they Live in Rebellion against Him, <hi>Wo unto them!</hi> Show them, from, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. That since they are <hi>Baptised, into the Name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit,</hi> they must <hi>observe all Things, whatsoever</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ <hi>has Commanded them.</hi> Show them, from Rom. 6.4. That since they are <hi>Baptised,</hi> they are <hi>Buried with Christ in Baptism,</hi> and must <hi>Live no longer in Sin,</hi> but be <hi>Dead</hi> unto all the Vanities of the World. Show them from Gal. 3.27. That since they are <hi>Baptised,</hi> they have <hi>put on Christ,</hi> and must follow His <hi>Example,</hi> and be as <hi>He was in the World.</hi> Show them from 1 Pet. 3 21. That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Baptised,</hi> they must now make <hi>the Answer of a Good Conscience,</hi> to all the proposals of the <hi>New-Covenant:</hi> and God propounding to them, <hi>Shall my Christ be thine, and wilt thou be His?</hi> they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104904:9"/>must conscientiously answer, <hi>Lord, with all my Heart!</hi> Put this very solemnly unto your Children; <hi>My Child, Shall God the Father, be thy Father? Shall God the Son, be thy Saviour! Shall God the Spirit, be thy Sanctifier; And art thou willing to be the Servant of that one God, who is, Father, Son, and Spirit?</hi> Leave them not, until their little Hearts are conquered unto <hi>That</hi> for which they have been <hi>Baptised.</hi> It has been the Judgment of some Judicious men; <hi>That if Infant Baptism were more Improved, it would be less Disputed.</hi> O that it were thus <hi>Improved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>III. Instruct</hi> your <hi>Children</hi> in the Great Matters of <hi>Salvation;</hi> O <hi>Parents,</hi> don't let them <hi>Dy without Instruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is indeed, an <hi>Instruction</hi> in <hi>Civil</hi> Matters, which we owe unto our <hi>Children.</hi> 'Tis very pleasing to our Lord Jesus Christ, that our <hi>Children</hi> should be well formed with, and well-informed in the Rules of <hi>Civility,</hi> and not be left a <hi>Clownish,</hi> and <hi>Sottish,</hi> and <hi>Ill-bred</hi> sort of Creatures. An Unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly Brood is a Dishonour to <hi>Religion.</hi> And there are many points of a <hi>Good
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104904:10"/>Education,</hi> that we should bestow upon our <hi>Children;</hi> They should <hi>Read,</hi> and <hi>Write,</hi> and <hi>Cyphar,</hi> and be put unto some Agreeable <hi>Callings;</hi> and not only our <hi>Sons,</hi> but our <hi>Daughters</hi> also should be taught such <hi>Things,</hi> as will afterwards make them Useful in their places. There is a little <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> laid in such an <hi>Education.</hi> But besides, and beyond all this, there is an <hi>Instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion</hi> in <hi>Divine</hi> Matters, which our <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> are to be made partakers of. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Instruct</hi> your <hi>Children,</hi> in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of <hi>Religion;</hi> and acquaint them, with God, and Christ, and the Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Gospel, and the Doctrines and Methods of the <hi>Great Salvation.</hi> It was Required, in Psal. 78.5. <hi>He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded our Fathers, to make known to their Children, that the Generation to come might know, who should arise and declare them to their Children, that they might set their Hope in God, and keep His Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> It was Required in Eph. 6.4. <hi>Fathers, bring up your Children in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord.</hi> Would you have your <hi>Children</hi> to be <hi>Wise</hi> and <hi>Good?</hi> I know not why you should expect it, unless you take abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104904:10"/>of pains, by your <hi>Instruction</hi> to make them so. There was a <hi>Wise</hi> and a <hi>Good</hi> Son, who gave that Account, how he became what he was; in Prov. 4.3, 4. <hi>I was my Fathers Son, and he Taught me.</hi> O Begin betimes, to Tell your Children, <hi>who</hi> is their <hi>Maker,</hi> and <hi>who</hi> is their <hi>Saviour,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> they are <hi>Themselves,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> is like to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them; and by no means let them want that Advantage, in 2. Tim. 3.15 <hi>From a Child thou hast known the Holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wise unto Salvation.</hi> Cause them to look often into their <hi>Bibles,</hi> and here and there Single out some special <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> from those <hi>Oracles</hi> of Heaven for them to get into their <hi>memories.</hi> And for the better management of their <hi>Instruction,</hi> there are especially Two <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,</hi> to be laid Hold upon; the one is, a Proper <hi>Catechism,</hi> the other is the Publick <hi>Ministry.</hi> Be sure, that they Learn their <hi>Catechism</hi> very perfectly; But then content not your selves with hearing them say by Rote, the <hi>Answers</hi> in their <hi>Catechism; Question</hi> them very distinctly over again about every clause in the <hi>Answers;</hi> and bring all to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> so
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104904:11"/>plain before them, that by their saying only, <hi>Yes,</hi> or, <hi>No,</hi> you may perceive that the sense of the Truth is Entred into their Souls. And then, what they hear in the Evangelical <hi>Ministry,</hi> do you Apply it unto them after their coming Home; Confer with them familiarly about the Things that have been hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the <hi>Ministry</hi> of the Word: Go over one Thing after another, with them, till you see they have got clear <hi>Idoeas</hi> of it; Then put it unto them, <hi>Are not you now to Avoid such a thing;</hi> or, <hi>to perform such a thing!</hi> And, <hi>must not you now make such and such a prayer unto God?</hi> Bid them then, go do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. Hence also, 'Twere very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sireable, that you should <hi>watch</hi> all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unities, to be instilling your <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> into the Souls of your little Folks. They are <hi>narrow-mouth'd</hi> Vessels, and things must be <hi>drop after drop</hi> instill'd into them. It was required in Deut. 6.6, 7. <hi>The words which I command thee, Thou shalt teach them Diligently unto thy Children, and shalt Talk of them, when thou sittest in thine House, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up.</hi> How
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104904:11"/>often in a week, are we Diverting our selves, with our <hi>Children</hi> in our <hi>Houses?</hi> There they stand before us; There is nothing to hinder our saving some ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable Thing for them to think upon; Well, can you let fall <hi>Nothing</hi> upon them, that it will be worth their while, for them to think upon? What, <hi>Nothing</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> and of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>World,</hi> and of their own <hi>Souls,</hi> and of the <hi>Sins</hi> that may Endanger them, and of the Wayes which they may take to be Happy? Doubtless, you may say <hi>something.</hi> And who can tell? It may be, after you are gone to behold the Face of the Lord Jesus Christ in Glory, these your <hi>Children</hi> will Remember Hundreds of profitable <hi>Instructions,</hi> that you have given 'em; and <hi>Live</hi> upon them when you that gave 'em, are <hi>Dead.</hi> With Two Strokes I will clench this Advice. The one is that in Prov. 22.6. <hi>Train up a Child in the way he should go, and when he is old, he will not Depart from it.</hi> The other is that in Prov. 17.25. <hi>A Foolish Son is a grief to his Father, and a bitterness to her that bare him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104904:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>W. Parents,</hi> With a <hi>Sweet Authority</hi> over your <hi>Children, <hi>Rebuke</hi>
                  </hi> them for, and <hi>Restrain</hi> them from, every thing that may prove prejudicial unto their <hi>Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Syrs, You can do little for the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of your <hi>Children,</hi> if once you have lost your <hi>Authority</hi> over them. Would you bring your <hi>Children</hi> to the Fear of God? Your character then must be that, in 1 Tim. 3.4. <hi>One that Ruleth well his own Bouse, having his Children in subjection, with all Gravity.</hi> Don't by your Lightness and Weakness and Folly, suffer them to Trample upon you; but keep up so much <hi>Authority,</hi> that your <hi>Word</hi> may be a <hi>Law</hi> unto them. Nevertheless, Let not your <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> be strained with such <hi>Harshness,</hi> and <hi>Fierceness,</hi> as may discourage your <hi>Children.</hi> To treat our <hi>Children</hi> like <hi>Slaves,</hi> and with such Rigour, that they shall always <hi>Tremble</hi> and <hi>Abhor</hi> to come into our presence, <hi>This</hi> will be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to our <hi>Heavenly Father.</hi> Our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> should be so Tempered with Kindness, and Meekness, and Loving Tenderness, that our Children may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104904:12"/>
                  <hi>Fear</hi> us with <hi>Delight,</hi> and see that we <hi>Love</hi> them, with as much <hi>Delight.</hi> Now, Let our <hi>Authority,</hi> effectually keep in our <hi>Children,</hi> from all their unruly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancies and Extravagancies. If we let our Young Folks grow <hi>Head-strong,</hi> and if we grow Afraid of compelling them to the <hi>Wholesome Orders</hi> of our Families, we have even given them up to Ruine. God brought that Son to an Untimely and a Terrible End, of whom 'tis reported, in 1 King. 1.6. <hi>His Father had not Displeased him at any time, in saying, Why hast thou done so?</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, <hi>Parents,</hi> Interpose your <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> to stop and check the Carrier of your <hi>Children,</hi> when they will be running into the <hi>paths of the Destroyer.</hi> Gratily them with <hi>Rewards</hi> of <hi>Well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> when they <hi>Do well;</hi> but let them not be gratified with every Ungodly <hi>Vanity,</hi> that their <hi>Vain Minds</hi> may be set upon. Wherefore keep a strict <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection</hi> upon their <hi>Conversations;</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, How they spend their <hi>Time?</hi> Examine, What <hi>Company</hi> they keep? Examine, Whether they take no <hi>Bad Courses?</hi> Be not such Foolish <hi>Enemies</hi> to your selves, and your <hi>Children,</hi> as to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104904:13"/>count them your <hi>Enemies,</hi> that shall Friendlily advise you of their Miscarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. That <hi>wretched Folly,</hi> is a very <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent One!</hi> When you Find out their Miscarriages, effectually <hi>Rebuke</hi> them, and <hi>Restrain</hi> them. Incurr not the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of Heaven, once Incurr'd by a Fond Father, in 1 Sam. 3.13. <hi>I will Judge his House for ever, for the Iniquity which he knoweth; because his Sons made themselves vile, and he Restrained them not.</hi> Ah, Thou Indulgent Parent; If thou canst not <hi>Cross</hi> thy <hi>Children,</hi> when they are disposed unto that which is for the Dishonour of God, God will make thy <hi>Children</hi> to become <hi>Crosses</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. Syrs, When your <hi>Children</hi> do amiss, call them Aside; set before them the <hi>Precepts</hi> of God which they have broken, and the <hi>Threatnings</hi> of God, which they provoked. Demand of them, to profess their Sorrow for their <hi>Fault,</hi> and Resolve that they will be no more so <hi>Faulty.</hi> Yea, There may be occasion for you, to consider that Word of God, in Prov. 13.24. <hi>He that spareth his Rod, hateth his Son, but he that loveth him, chasteneth him betimes;</hi> and that Word, in Prov. 19.18. <hi>Chasten thy Son,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104904:13"/>while there is Hope, and let not thy Soul spare for his Crying;</hi> and that word, in Prov. 23.13, 14. <hi>Withold not Correction from the Child; for if thou beatest him with the Rod, he shall not Dy; Thou shalt beat him with the Rod, and shalt deliver his Soul from Hell.</hi> But if it must be so, Remember this Counsil; Never give a Blow in a <hi>passion.</hi> Stay till your <hi>passion</hi> is over; and let the Offendors plainly see, that you deal thus with them, out of pure <hi>Obedience</hi> unto God, and for their true <hi>Repentance.</hi> One of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, has this Ingenious gloss. In the Tabernacle, <hi>Aarons Rod,</hi> and the Pot of <hi>Manna,</hi> were together; so (saies he) when the <hi>Rod</hi> is used, the sweetness and goodness of the <hi>Manna</hi> must accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it: and <hi>Mercy</hi> be joined with <hi>Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> Let me leave that praemonition with you, in Prov. 29.15. <hi>A Child left unto himself, bringeth his Mother to shame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>V.</hi> Lay your <hi>Charges</hi> upon your <hi>Children; Parents, Charge</hi> them to <hi>Work about their own Salvation.</hi> The <hi>Charges</hi> of <hi>Parents</hi> have a great Efficacy upon many <hi>Children;</hi> To <hi>Charge</hi> 'em vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently, is to <hi>Charm</hi> 'em wonderfully.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104904:14"/>
                  <hi>Command</hi> your <hi>Children,</hi> and it may be they will <hi>Obey.</hi> Let <hi>Gods</hi> Commands be <hi>your</hi> Commands, and it may be your <hi>Children</hi> will <hi>obey</hi> them. Lay upon your <hi>Children,</hi> the <hi>Charges</hi> of God, as <hi>David</hi> once upon his, in 1 Chron. 28.9. <hi>My Son, know thou the God of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and serve Him with a perfect heart, and with a willing mind; if thou seek Him, He will be found of thee, but if thou forsake Him, He will cast thee off for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, Syrs, You will do well, to fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle out some singular <hi>Charges</hi> of God, and calling your <hi>Children</hi> one by one before you, Lay those <hi>Charges</hi> upon them, in the Name of the God that made them, and obtain from them, if you can, a promise that they will Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve those <hi>Charges,</hi> with the Help of that God. I'l set before you, Three or Four of those <hi>Charges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let one of your <hi>Charges</hi> upon your <hi>Children,</hi> be That in 1 Joh. 3.23. <hi>This is His Commandment, that we should Believe on the Name of His Son Jesus Christ. Charge</hi> them to carry their poor, guilty, ignorant and polluted and Enslaved Souls, unto the Lord Jesus Christ, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104904:14"/>He may <hi>Save</hi> them from <hi>their Sins,</hi> and <hi>Save</hi> them from the <hi>Wrath to come. Charge</hi> them, to mind how the Lord Jesus Christ Executes the Office of a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>Priest,</hi> and a <hi>King,</hi> and Cry to Him, that He would Save them in the Execution of all those Blessed Offices.</p>
               <p>Let another of your <hi>Charges</hi> be that in Hag. 1.5, 7. <hi>Thus saith the Lord of Hosts, Consider your Wayes. Charge</hi> them to set apart a few minutes now and then, for <hi>Consideration;</hi> and in those minutes, <hi>Charge</hi> them to <hi>Consider,</hi> what they have been doing, and what they should have been doing, ever since they came into the World, &amp; if they should immediately go out of the World, what will become of them throughout Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ages. I have Read of a <hi>Dying Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> who laid this <hi>Charge</hi> upon his wild <hi>Son,</hi> That he would allow one quarter of an Hour every Day to <hi>Consider</hi> on something or other, any Thing, as his Fancy led him. The Young man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for some while done so, at last began to <hi>consider,</hi> why his <hi>Dying Parent</hi> should lay such a <hi>Charge</hi> upon him This brought on so many Devout
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104904:15"/>Thoughts, that e're long, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of the Young man, the Desire of the <hi>Dying Parent</hi> was accomplished. Oh! If you could Engage your <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> to <hi>Think upon their Wayes,</hi> there would be Hopes of their <hi>Turning to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, Let a Third of your <hi>Charges,</hi> be that in Mat. 6.6. <hi>Enter into thy Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set, and when thou hast shut thy Door, pray to thy Father that sees in secret. Charge</hi> them to Retire for <hi>Secret Prayer,</hi> every Day that comes over their Heads. Talk with them, till you see, that they can tell, what they should <hi>pray</hi> for: And then, often <hi>charge</hi> them to <hi>pray</hi> every day; yea, sometimes <hi>Ask</hi> them, <hi>Do you Remember the charge I Laid upon you?</hi> Ah, Parent, Thy <hi>Children</hi> will do well, while it can be said, <hi>Behold, They pray.</hi> And thy House filled with thy <hi>Childrens Prayers,</hi> would be better accommodated, than i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it were filled, with all the Riches of the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let a Fourth of your <hi>Charges</hi> be That, in Prov. 9.6. <hi>Forsake the Foolish and Live. Charge</hi> them to avoid the snares of <hi>Evil Company;</hi> Terrify them with Warnings of those Deadly Snares.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104904:15"/>Often Repeat this <hi>Charge</hi> unto them, That if there be any <hi>Vicious Company,</hi> they shun them, as they would the <hi>Plague</hi> or the <hi>Devil.</hi> Often say, <hi>My Son, if Sinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs entice thee, consent thou not.</hi> Often say, <hi>My Child, Walk with the Wise, and thou shalt be wise, but a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of Fools shall be destroyed.</hi> Oh, Don't let the <hi>Beasts</hi> of prey, carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy <hi>Children</hi> alive.</p>
               <p>Shall I add; It is here intimated, That an <hi>Abraham,</hi> is to <hi>Command</hi> his <hi>Children,</hi> very particularly, about, <hi>The Way of the Lord. The Way of the Lord,</hi> is the <hi>Way</hi> of his Right, pure, <hi>Instituted Worship.</hi> Well then, <hi>Command</hi> your <hi>Children,</hi> That they don't Forsake the Holy <hi>Institutions</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, and Embrace a <hi>Vain Worship,</hi> consisting of Things that <hi>He</hi> never In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted. There are some clauses in the <hi>Second Commandment,</hi> which inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, That if <hi>Tarents</hi> would see the <hi>Mercies</hi> of God upon their <hi>Children,</hi> they must <hi>Charge</hi> them, to Worship God, only in those <hi>Wayes,</hi> of Worship, that God hath Appointed.</p>
               <p>Thus keep <hi>Charging</hi> of your <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> while you <hi>Live.</hi> And, if you are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104904:16"/>capable so to Do, Do it once more with all possible Solemnity, when you come to <hi>Dy.</hi> The words of a <hi>Dying Parent,</hi> will probably be <hi>Living</hi> Words, and <hi>Lively</hi> Ones. When our Excellent <hi>Mitchel</hi> was a Dying, he let fall such a Speech as This, unto a Young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that Lodg'd in his House, <hi>My Friend, As a Dying man, I now charge you, that you don't meet me out of Christ in the Day of Christ.</hi> This one Speech, brought into Christ, the Soul of that <hi>Young Gentleman!</hi> Truly, If your <hi>Dying Lips,</hi> may utter such <hi>Dying Words</hi> unto your <hi>Children,</hi> who can tell, but they may then be brought into <hi>Christ,</hi> if they were never so before! But, lest you should have no opportunity to <hi>Speak</hi> in a <hi>Dying Hour,</hi> why should you not <hi>Write</hi> such Things, as you would have them to Think upon, when you shall be <hi>Dead</hi> and Gone? An unknown deal of Good, may your <hi>Children</hi> Reap, from the Admonitions, that a <hi>Dying Parent</hi> may Leave unto them.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>VI. Parents,</hi> Be <hi>Exemplary:</hi> Your <hi>Example</hi> may do much towards the <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of your <hi>Children,</hi> Your <hi>Works</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104904:16"/>will more <hi>Work</hi> upon your <hi>Children,</hi> than your <hi>Words;</hi> Your <hi>Patterns</hi> will do more than your <hi>Precepts;</hi> your <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies</hi> than your <hi>Counsils.</hi> What was then said unto <hi>Pastors,</hi> may very fitly be said unto <hi>Parents,</hi> in Tit. 2.2. <hi>In all Things show thy self a pattern of good works;</hi> &amp; in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Be thou an Example in Word, in Conversation, in Charity, in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in Faith, in Purity.</hi> 'Twill be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for you to infuse any Good, into your <hi>Children,</hi> if you appear void of that Good your selves. If the <hi>Old Crab</hi> go backward, it is to no purpose, for the <hi>Young One</hi> to be directed unto going forward: Syrs, <hi>Young Ones,</hi> will Crawl after the <hi>Old Ones.</hi> Would you have your <hi>Children,</hi> well principled with the <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> of God? Mind that passage, in Act. 10.2. <hi>Cornelius was a devout man, and one that Feared God, with all his House.</hi> Mind that passage, in Act. 18.8 <hi>Crispus Believed on the Lord, with all his House.</hi> It seems, the whole <hi>House,</hi> is like to do, as the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> do. 'Tis, as <hi>Austin</hi> expresses it, the usual Cry, <hi>Nolumus esse meliores quam patres,</hi> We will be no Better than our <hi>Parents.</hi> If the <hi>Parents</hi> will <hi>make their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104904:17"/>Cakes to the Queen of Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> will <hi>kindle</hi> their <hi>Fires</hi> for them. <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> somewhere Enquires why the Prophet <hi>Elisha</hi> imprecated the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges of Heaven upon the <hi>Children</hi> that mocked him, when they hardly understood what they did? And he answers, <hi>The Children Learnt their wicked Language from their Parents, and now God punished both of them together. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> Let your <hi>Children</hi> see nothing by you, but what shall be commendable and imitable. Be able to say unto your <hi>Children, My Child, Follow me, as you have seen me follow Christ.</hi> Let them from <hi>your</hi> Seriousness, and <hi>your</hi> Prayerfulness, and <hi>your</hi> Watchfulness, and <hi>your</hi> Sanctification of the Lords-Day, be taught, how <hi>they</hi> should <hi>walk and please God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You <hi>Bid</hi> them do well; <hi>Show</hi> them <hi>How!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>VII. <hi>Prayer, Prayer,</hi>
                  </hi> must be the <hi>Crown</hi> of all: <hi>Parents,</hi> Is it your Hearts <hi>Desire?</hi> Let it be also your <hi>Prayer,</hi> for your <hi>Children,</hi> that they <hi>may be Saved. Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Salvation</hi> of any Sinners, <hi>availeth much.</hi> How much may it <hi>avail</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104904:17"/>for the <hi>Salvation</hi> of our Sinful <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren?</hi> Much <hi>avail'd</hi> that <hi>Prayer</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> in 1 Chron. 29.19. <hi>Lord, Give unto my Son a perfect Heart, to keep thy Commandments. Parents,</hi> Make such a <hi>Prayer</hi> for your <hi>Children, Lord, Give unto my Child, a New Heart, and a Clean Heart, and a Soft Heart; and an Heart after thy own Heart.</hi> We have been told, That <hi>Children</hi> once were brought unto our Lord Jesus Christ, for Him to <hi>put His Hands</hi> upon them; and <hi>He put His Hands upon them, and Blessed them.</hi> Oh! Thrice, and Four Times <hi>Blessed Children!</hi> Well, <hi>Parent,</hi> Bring thy <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> unto the Lord Jesus Christ; It may be, He will put His <hi>Blessing,</hi> and <hi>Healing,</hi> and <hi>Saving Hands</hi> upon them: <hi>Then,</hi> They are <hi>Blessed,</hi> and shall be <hi>Blessed</hi> for evermore! If <hi>Abraham</hi> Cry to God, <hi>O that my Son Ishmael may Live in thy sight!</hi> God will say to <hi>Abraham, Concerning Ishmael, I have heard Thee! Pray</hi> for the <hi>Salvation</hi> of thy <hi>Children,</hi> and carry the Names of every one of them, every day before the Lord, with <hi>Prayers,</hi> the <hi>Cries</hi> whereof shall pierce the very Heavens. Holy <hi>Job</hi> did so! Job 1.5. <hi>He offered according to the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104904:18"/>of all his Children; Thus did Job con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</hi> Address Heaven with daily <hi>Prayers,</hi> That God would make thy <hi>Children</hi> the <hi>Temples</hi> of <hi>His Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Vessels</hi> of His <hi>Glory;</hi> and the <hi>Care</hi> of His Holy <hi>Angels.</hi> Address the Lord Jesus Christ, with <hi>Prayers,</hi> like them of old, That all the <hi>Maladies</hi> upon the Souls of thy <hi>Children</hi> may be cured, and that the <hi>Evil One</hi> may have no possession of them. Yea, When thou dost cast thine Eyes upon the Little Folks, often in a day dart up an <hi>Ejaculatory Prayer</hi> to Heaven for them; <hi>Lord, Let this Child be thy Servant for ever.</hi> If thy <hi>Prayers</hi> are not presently answered, be not thereby Disheartened: Remember the Word of the Lord, in Luk. 18.1. <hi>That men ought always to pray, and not to Faint.</hi> Redouble thy <hi>Importunity,</hi> until thou speed for thy Child, as the poor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Canaan</hi> did. Join <hi>Fasting</hi> to thy <hi>Prayer;</hi> It may be, <hi>The Evil in the Soul of thy Child, will not go out, without such a Remedy. David</hi> betakes himself to <hi>Fasting,</hi> as well as <hi>Prayer,</hi> for the <hi>Life</hi> of his <hi>Child.</hi> Oh, Do as much for the <hi>Soul</hi> of thy <hi>Child! Wrestle</hi> with the Lord. Receive no <hi>Denial.</hi> Earnestly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104904:18"/>protest, <hi>Lord, I will not let thee go, except thou Bless this poor Child of mine, and make it thy own!</hi> Do thus, until, if it may be, thy Heart is Raised by a Touch of Heaven, to a <hi>particular Faith; That God has blessed this Child, and it shall be Blessed and Saved for ever.</hi> But is this all that is to be done? There is more. Parents, <hi>Pray with</hi> your <hi>Children,</hi> as well as <hi>for</hi> them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Family prayer</hi> must be mentained by all those <hi>Parents,</hi> that would not have their <hi>Children</hi> miss of <hi>Salvation,</hi> and that would not have the <hi>Damnation</hi> of their <hi>Children</hi> horribly fall upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Man, Thy <hi>Family</hi> is a <hi>Pagan Family,</hi> if it be a <hi>Prayerless Family:</hi> And the <hi>Children</hi> going down to the <hi>place of Dragons</hi> from this thy <hi>Family,</hi> will pour out their Execrations upon Thee, in the Bottom of Hell, until the very Heavens be no more.</p>
               <p>But, besides your <hi>Family Prayers,</hi> O <hi>Parents,</hi> why should you not now and then, take one capable <hi>Child</hi> after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, alone before the Lord? Carry the <hi>Child</hi> with you, into your <hi>Secret Chambers;</hi> make the <hi>Child</hi> kneel down by you, while you present it unto the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104904:19"/>Lord, and Implore His Blessing upon it. Let the <hi>Child,</hi> hear the Groans, &amp; see the Tears, and be a witness of the Agonies, wherewith you are <hi>Travailing</hi> for the Salvation of it. The <hi>Children</hi> will never Forget what you do; It will have a marvellous Force upon them.</p>
               <p>Thus, O <hi>Parents,</hi> You have been told, what you have to do, for the <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of your <hi>Children;</hi> and certainly, their <hi>Salvation</hi> is worth all of this!</p>
               <p>Your <hi>Zeal</hi> about the <hi>Salvation</hi> of your <hi>Children,</hi> will be a symptome of your own <hi>Sincerity.</hi> A total want of that <hi>Zeal,</hi> will be a <hi>Spot</hi> upon you, that is not a <hi>Spot of the Children of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God will Reward the <hi>Zeal.</hi> 'Tis very probable, That the <hi>Children</hi> thus cared for, will be the <hi>Saved</hi> of the Lord. Your <hi>Glad Hearts</hi> will one day see it, if they are so: 'Twill augment your <hi>Heaven,</hi> thro' all Eternity, to have <hi>These</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> with you.</p>
               <p>And let it be Remembred, That the <hi>Fathers,</hi> are not the only <hi>Parents</hi> obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thus to pursue the <hi>Salvation</hi> of their <hi>Children:</hi> You that are <hi>Mothers,</hi> have not a little to do for the <hi>Souls</hi> of your
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104904:19"/>
                  <hi>Children,</hi> and you have <hi>Opportunity</hi> to do more than a Little. <hi>Bathsheba</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Eunice</hi> the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of <hi>Timothy,</hi> did greatly Contribute unto the <hi>Salvation</hi> of their famous and worthy <hi>Sons.</hi> God has Commanded <hi>Children, Forsake not the Law of thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> Then, a <hi>Mother</hi> must give the <hi>Law</hi> of God unto them. 'Tis said of the Vertuous <hi>Woman, She Looks well to the Wayes of her Houshold;</hi> Then, a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Mother Looks well to the Wayes of her Children.</hi> Your <hi>Children</hi> may say, <hi>In Sin did my Mother Conceive me.</hi> Oh, Then Let <hi>Mothers</hi> do what they can, to <hi>Save</hi> their Children out of <hi>Sin.</hi> And especially, <hi>Mothers,</hi> Do you <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail</hi> for your <hi>Children</hi> over again, with your Earnest <hi>Prayers</hi> for their <hi>Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> until it may be said unto you, as it was unto <hi>Monica</hi> the Mother of <hi>Austin,</hi> concerning him; <hi>'Tis impossible, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy Child should perish, after thou hast Employ'd so many Prayers and Tears for the Salvation of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, God give a Good Success to these poor Endeavours!</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:104904:20"/>
            <head>THE Duties of CHILDREN To their Parents.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>DEUT. XXVII. 14, 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Levites shall speak, and shall say unto all the Men of Israel, with a loud voice:</p>
                  <p>Cursed is he that setteth Light, by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or his Mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Am going to Entertain you with a Discourse, that cannot have a fitter praeface, than those words, in Psal. 34.11. <hi>Come, ye Children, Hearken unto me, I will teach you the Fear of the Lord.</hi> The <hi>Children</hi> of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104904:20"/>are now appearing among, us; Yea, Our <hi>Little Ones</hi> are no <hi>Little part</hi> of the Assembly. And very many of these, are the <hi>Children</hi> of pious <hi>Parents,</hi> the <hi>Children</hi> whose Piety has therefore been fervently desired and required by their <hi>Parents. Come, ye Children, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to me;</hi> I will tell you, what you shall do, that your <hi>Parents</hi> may be Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in you, and that your own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness may be secured and increased.</p>
            <p>There was a Solemnity sometimes observed upon the Two Mountains of <hi>Ebal,</hi> and <hi>Gerizzim,</hi> in the Land of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> On the Top of Mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> there stood <hi>Six</hi> of the Israelitish Tribes, and <hi>Six</hi> on the Top of Mount <hi>Geriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zim.</hi> Certain Levites with the Ark of God, in the Valley between them, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting themselves unto Mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> with a Loud Voice, uttered very Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly, no less than Twelve terrible <hi>Curses;</hi> unto which the Tribes on that Mount, made the very Heavens ring, with a dreadful, <hi>Amen,</hi> unto them. But between each of these <hi>Curses,</hi> the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites directed themselves unto Mount <hi>Gerizzim,</hi> with <hi>Blessings</hi> directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed unto those <hi>Curses;</hi> and the Tribes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104904:21"/>on that Mount, gave the Shout of a Joyful, <hi>Amen,</hi> upon them. 'Tis true, the Order prescribing the <hi>Blessings,</hi> is not so distinctly Recited by <hi>Moses,</hi> as that of the <hi>Curses;</hi> because 'tis Reserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Special Glory of our Blessed Lord Jesus Christ, and of His <hi>Glorious Gospel,</hi> to bring in the <hi>Blessings</hi> of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Until the <hi>Gospel</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ arrive unto us, the <hi>Law</hi> does pronounce unto us nothing but <hi>Curses,</hi> we hear nothing but a <hi>Thunder of Wrath Cursing</hi> of us</p>
            <p>The Second of the Direful <hi>Curses,</hi> which the <hi>Levites</hi> of God, facing to Mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> pronounced was, <hi>Cursed be he that sets Light by his Father or his Mother.</hi> Doubtless, when the vast Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of people, as one man, replied, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> upon it, it sounded like an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Thunder-clap. Yea, but the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-clap is not yet over; the peals of it, are this very Day to be again Sounded, in the midst of you, O Congregation of God. We read, that when the thing thus Appointed, was first observ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the Tribes of <hi>Israel,</hi> in the Days of <hi>Joshua,</hi> [Josh. 8.35.] There were the <hi>Little Ones,</hi> in the <hi>Congregation.</hi> It
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104904:21"/>is not amiss, that there are so many <hi>Little Ones,</hi> in the Great <hi>Congregation</hi> here come together; and unto <hi>Them</hi> especially, am I now to bring that Warning from God.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>The Heavy Curse of God, will fall upon those Children, that make Light of their Parents.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>To <hi>Set Light</hi> by ones <hi>Parents,</hi> is in other words, to Treat them with any Ungodly <hi>Contempt:</hi> And, you mind it, <hi>My Children,</hi> that the <hi>Curse</hi> of God is denounced, not only upon <hi>Children,</hi> which cast Contempt upon their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:</hi> Oftentimes the <hi>Fathers</hi> have the Wisdom to keep up their Authority, and keep themselves above the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of their <hi>Children.</hi> But the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> do more frequently by their Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Weakness, bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, the <hi>Contempt</hi> of their <hi>Children,</hi> and Lay themselves Low, by many Impertinencies, Now, behold, the Admonition of Heaven; the <hi>Children</hi> which cast Contempt upon their <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> do also bring themselves under the <hi>Curse</hi> of God.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104904:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Curse of God!</hi> The Terriblest Thing that ever was heard of; The <hi>First born of Terribles!</hi> Can I mention this Tremendous Thing, <hi>The Curse of God;</hi> and, Oh, My Children, Will not you Tremble at it? Who can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear crying out, as <hi>Elihu</hi> did, when he heard the Thunders of God ratling in the Heavens over him, <hi>At this my heart even Trembles, and it is moved out of its place!</hi> I hope, none of you are come to such a Degree of Atheism, as to Defy, the <hi>Curse of God:</hi> You won't <hi>mock at the Fear</hi> of the most Fearful Thing, in the World. But give me your Attention, while I do from the Oracles of the Almighty God, handle that CASE among you.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <head>CASE. <hi>What Respects to their <hi>Parents</hi> must be rendred by the <hi>Children,</hi> that would not by Affronts to their Parents, bring down upon themselves the dreadful <hi>Curses</hi> of God?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Lessons, which I have now to let you, <hi>My Children,</hi> be these.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:104904:22"/>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>I.</hi> Maintain in your own Spirits, a Dread of those Dreadful <hi>Curses,</hi> with which the God of Heaven uses to take <hi>Vengeance</hi> on the <hi>Children,</hi> who put not <hi>Respect,</hi> but <hi>Contempt,</hi> upon their <hi>Parents.</hi> Behold, how dreadfully the <hi>Judgments</hi> of God follow the Children that <hi>Set Light by their Parents;</hi> and Oh, my <hi>Warned</hi> Children, upon the sight of those Warnings, cry out, <hi>Lord, my Flesh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles for fear, and I am afraid of those Judgments!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed there is no Sin more usually Revenged, with the Sensible and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Curses</hi> of God, than that Sin, <hi>The Contempt of Parents.</hi> Exasperated <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> themselves, do sometimes Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>Curses</hi> upon their <hi>Children;</hi> and the the Invisible World with a strange, but a quick work, usually saies, <hi>Amen,</hi> to those <hi>Curses.</hi> But, I beseech of you, O <hi>Parents,</hi> that be your <hi>Exasperations</hi> what they will, you forbear to use any <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations</hi> on your <hi>Children.</hi> Alas, They will be <hi>Cursed Children</hi> fast enough, without the least Ill wish of yours to hasten it. When it was Instituted, that the Levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es were to proclaim, <hi>Cursed is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104904:23"/>he that sets Light by his Father, or his Mother,</hi> One part of the Institution was, <hi>All the people shall say, Amen.</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it often comes to pass, that when the <hi>Curses</hi> of God come upon them that set Light by their <hi>Parents,</hi> it shall be so, that <hi>all the people</hi> shall take Notice of it; <hi>all the people</hi> shall see an, <hi>Amen,</hi> set unto it, shall see it <hi>Ratified. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> I must be a little particular with you.</p>
               <p>First. <hi>Undutiful Children,</hi> for the <hi>Sin</hi> of the <hi>Contempt</hi> they cast upon their <hi>Parents,</hi> are often <hi>Cursed</hi> by God, with being Left unto yet <hi>more Sin</hi> against Him. I could not have spoken a more Terrible word! This is most certain, The more <hi>Sinful</hi> any man is, the more <hi>Cursed</hi> is that man. It is an amazing <hi>Vengeance</hi> of God, that gives a Sinner up to Sin for Sin, and <hi>Curses</hi> a Sinner for one Sin, by Leaving him to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But Undutiful Children, are commonly <hi>Cursed,</hi> and Banned by such a <hi>Vengeance</hi> of God. We read of some Sinners, whom the Justice of God, gives up to <hi>Sin;</hi> and this is one Brand upon those doleful Sinners, in Rom. 1.30. <hi>Disobedient unto Parents.</hi> The <hi>Fifth</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104904:23"/>Commandment stands in the Front of all the <hi>Six,</hi> upon the <hi>Second Table</hi> of the Law. <hi>Children,</hi> If you break the <hi>Fifth</hi> Commandment, there is not much Likelihood, that you will keep the rest; No, there is Hazard, that the <hi>Curse</hi> of God, will give you up to break every one of them all. <hi>Undutiful Children</hi> soon become horrid Creatures, for <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chastity,</hi> for <hi>Dishonesty,</hi> for <hi>Lying,</hi> and all manner of Abominations: And the <hi>Contempt</hi> which they cast upon the Advice of their <hi>Parents,</hi> is one thing that pulls down this <hi>Curse</hi> of God upon them. They who Sin against their <hi>Parents,</hi> are sometimes by God given up to Sin against <hi>all the world</hi> beside. Mind the most Scandalous Instances of Wickedness and Villany; You'l ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily find, they were first <hi>Undutiful Children,</hi> before they fell into the rest of their atrocious Wickedness.</p>
               <p>Secondly. <hi>Undutiful Children</hi> for the Contempt they cast upon their Parents, are often <hi>Cursed</hi> by God, with a <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief</hi> brought upon all their Affavrs. A Strange <hi>Disaster</hi> uses to follow <hi>Undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Children,</hi> much <hi>Evil pursues</hi> that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104904:24"/>kind of <hi>Sinners;</hi> there is a secret <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> of God, perplexing their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayrs; thro' that <hi>Vengeance</hi> of God, None of their Affayrs do prosper with them. When <hi>David</hi> was vexed with one of his <hi>Undutiful Children,</hi> he could foretel, in Psal. 55.19. <hi>God shall Afflict them.</hi> There is a <hi>Secret Blast</hi> of God, upon <hi>Undutiful Children.</hi> They are <hi>Afflicted</hi> in their <hi>Estates:</hi> It is the <hi>Curse</hi> of God upon them, for their being Lothe, to do what they could for their <hi>Parents,</hi> with their <hi>Estates.</hi> They are <hi>Afflicted</hi> in their <hi>Bodies:</hi> It is the <hi>Curse</hi> of God upon them, for their Disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring the <hi>Parents</hi> of their <hi>Bodies. God Afflicts</hi> them with <hi>Reproaches:</hi> 'Tis the <hi>Curse</hi> of God upon them; They have <hi>Reproached</hi> or <hi>Despised</hi> their <hi>Parents.</hi> They are followed with one plague af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, by the Irresistible Wrath, and <hi>Curse</hi> of God: They can't compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, how they come to be so plagued in all their Interests: 'Tis it may be their <hi>Contempt</hi> of their <hi>Parents,</hi> that has, been the <hi>Worm</hi> at the <hi>Root,</hi> which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses all to wither with 'em. And if these <hi>Undutiful Children,</hi> ever Live to have <hi>Children</hi> of their own, God pays
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104904:24"/>'em home in their <hi>own Coin;</hi> God pays 'em in the <hi>Undutifulness</hi> of their <hi>own Children;</hi> In the <hi>Undutifulness</hi> of their <hi>own Children,</hi> God makes 'em, to <hi>possess the Iniquities of their Youth. Judah,</hi> cast Contempt upon his <hi>Parents,</hi> by Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Canaanitess,</hi> as it should seem without their Consent: God <hi>Cursed</hi> this <hi>Judah</hi> with a couple of Children, who were such Wretches, that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Hand of Heaven, dispatch'd 'em out of the World. You have doubtless been in form'd of that famous History, in the <hi>Theatrum Historiae;</hi> A vile Son did once beat his old <hi>Father,</hi> and then Drag him to the Threshold of the House, by the Hair of the Head. Afterwards, when he grew <hi>Old himself,</hi> (which by the way, was a <hi>Rare Thing!</hi>) his own Son did in like manner beat <hi>him,</hi> and then Drag him also, by the Hair of the Head, not only to the Threshold, but out of the Doors, into the <hi>Dirt.</hi> Hereupon he cryed out with Anguish, <hi>Ah! If this Varlet had pull'd me only to the Threshold, I had been served, but just as my Father was by me!</hi> Children, Remember this.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104904:25"/>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Death;</hi> Yea, an <hi>Early Death,</hi> and a <hi>Woful Death,</hi> is not seldom the <hi>Curse</hi> of God upon <hi>Undutiful Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> for their being so. It is the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Precept, Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy Dayes may be long upon the Land.</hi> Mind it, Children; Your <hi>Dayes</hi> are not like to be <hi>long upon the Land,</hi> if you <hi>Set Light by your Father, or Mother.</hi> When <hi>Absalom,</hi> with his Crue, was manifesting a Bloody <hi>Undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulness,</hi> his offended Father praedicted thus much, <hi>That those bloody and crafty men, should not Live out half their Dayes.</hi> Why, he knew, that the very <hi>Finger</hi> of God, had once written as much as this comes to; <hi>That Children, which did not Honour their Parents, must not look to have their Dayes long in the Land.</hi> We have all heard the Fate of that <hi>Undutiful Absalom;</hi> now some Travellers Report, that in the place where <hi>Absalom</hi> was Buried, there is now a vast Heap of <hi>Stones,</hi> thus produced: It is customary for them, that go by the place, to throw a <hi>Stone</hi> upon it, using these words; <hi>Thus it shall be done unto the Son that Rebelleth against his Father.</hi> Stand still, O my Children,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104904:25"/>and Look with Horror upon the Grave of <hi>Absalom:</hi> Read there, and see the <hi>Curse</hi> of God upon the <hi>Unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Children</hi> that cast <hi>Contempt</hi> on the <hi>Parents,</hi> who have been the <hi>Instruments</hi> of their <hi>Life,</hi> do thereby, what, but make <hi>Forfeitures</hi> of their <hi>Life?</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>Children</hi> to reckon it one main Design, and Business, and priviledge of their <hi>Life,</hi> to be <hi>Comforts</hi> unto their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents:</hi> When they cease to do so, God with a direful <hi>Curse</hi> often gives that Order about them, <hi>Take away the Life of that Undutiful Creature! That Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture shall no longer Live in the World.</hi> It was an <hi>Edict</hi> of Heaven, in Exod. 21.17. <hi>He that curseth his Father or his Mother, shall surely be put unto Death.</hi> And what shall then be done unto the <hi>Children,</hi> that prove <hi>Curses</hi> unto their <hi>Father,</hi> or their <hi>Mother? Undutiful Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> are so; But the <hi>Curse</hi> of God puts them to <hi>Death</hi> for it: And because those <hi>Undutiful Children</hi> are <hi>Wicked over much,</hi> therefore they <hi>Dy before their Time.</hi> Yea, 'tis no unusual Thing for the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Undutiful Children,</hi> to be Embittered with some Extraordinary Circumstances of Confusion and Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104904:26"/>I tell you, O <hi>Undutiful Children;</hi> There is Danger, Lest you be so <hi>Cursed of God,</hi> as to be <hi>Hanged on a Tree,</hi> at the Last. It is Remarkable, That the most of them, who are Executed on the <hi>Gallows,</hi> do at their Executed on the <hi>Gallows,</hi> do at their Execution cry out of This: <hi>Oh, 'Tis my Undutifulness unto my Parents, 'Tis my Disobedience unto my Parents, that hath brought me unto this Lamentable End!</hi> It is a memorable passage, in Prov. 30.17. <hi>The Eye that mocks at his Father, and despises to obey his Mother, the Ravens of the Valley shall pick it out, and the young Eagles shall Eat it.</hi> It seems, an Untimely and a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Death, often Exposes the Carcases of those <hi>Children,</hi> to the Carnivorous Fowls of Heaven. There was a Law in <hi>Israel,</hi> Deut. 21.21. <hi>That the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Child should be put to Death.</hi> After <hi>Stoning,</hi> he was <hi>Hang'd</hi> up; for in <hi>Israel</hi> they <hi>Hang'd</hi> up none, till they had first otherwise kill'd him; and no doubt, his <hi>Corpse</hi> being taken down, as it was to be before <hi>Sun set,</hi> it was thrown into a Noted Pit, such an one as that, into which they threw the Corps of <hi>Judas</hi> over the Precipice; &amp; there the Fowls of Heaven prey'd upon it. <hi>Agur</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:104904:26"/>alludes to This; And we often see it so, that the <hi>Rebellious Child,</hi> is left of God, unto those Crimes, for which he is <hi>put to Death,</hi> e're it be long. More than so; <hi>Undutiful Children</hi> are <hi>Unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Children;</hi> And the <hi>Curse</hi> of God sometimes gives over <hi>Unnatural Children</hi> to commit the most <hi>Unnatural Murders.</hi> They have <hi>Murdered themselves,</hi> and been <hi>Self-Destroyers:</hi> and as they have Sinn'd against <hi>Nature,</hi> so they Dy the most <hi>against Nature,</hi> that can be. A Young man in this Country Drown'd himself; but he Left behind him, a Writing to his <hi>Father,</hi> wherein he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd, <hi>O Father, I have kept my Soul, as long as I could; My Ruine was the pride and stubbornness of my Tender Years!</hi> But is this all?</p>
               <p>No; Lastly; All the <hi>Curse</hi> of God upon <hi>Undutiful Children</hi> hitherto, is but the <hi>Death,</hi> riding the <hi>Pale Horse</hi> in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> whereof 'tis said, <hi>Hell fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</hi> I am after all to tell you, That the <hi>Vengeance of Eternal Fire,</hi> will be the portion of <hi>Undutiful Children</hi> after all; <hi>Children</hi> that cast <hi>Contempt</hi> upon their <hi>Parents,</hi> God will cast into the <hi>Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Eternal Fire</hi> at the Last, and into
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104904:27"/>
                  <hi>Everlasting Contempt.</hi> Surely, the <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> are the <hi>Cursed</hi> of God! Hear, O Children; If you are the <hi>Children of Rebellion,</hi> the <hi>Curse</hi> of God will make you the <hi>Children of Perdition,</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Eternal Ages. <hi>Undutiful Children,</hi> what are they, but the <hi>Children of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial?</hi> This is as much as to say, They are the <hi>Children of Satan;</hi> and unto <hi>Satan</hi> they shall go. The Bible has call'd 'em, <hi>The Children of the Devil;</hi> And whither shall the <hi>Children of the Devil</hi> go, but into the <hi>Everlasting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels?</hi> The <hi>Fiends of Darkness,</hi> will be the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> and the <hi>Eagles,</hi> that shall fasten their Talons, in the <hi>Eyes</hi> of those Children. When our Lord Jesus Christ, the <hi>Judge of the World,</hi> foretels, that in the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> having said unto those on His <hi>Right</hi> Hand, <hi>Come ye Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,</hi> He will say unto those on His <hi>Left</hi> Hand, <hi>Depart, ye Cursed, into Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Fire, with the Devil and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels;</hi> He seems to allude unto the Action between <hi>Gerizzim</hi> and <hi>Ebal.</hi> Truly, the <hi>Children</hi> Damn'd of old, upon Mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> for <hi>Setting Light</hi> by their <hi>Father</hi> or their <hi>Mother,</hi> will be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:104904:27"/>They, whom the Lord Jesus Christ, will one Day Doom, to <hi>Depart from Him into Everlasting Fire, with the Devil and his Angels.</hi> It was said, in Prov. 20.20. <hi>Whoso curseth his Father, or his Mother, his Lamp shall be put out in Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure Darkness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Children, If by <hi>Undutifulness</hi> to your <hi>Parents,</hi> you incur the <hi>Curse</hi> of God, it won't be Long before you go down into <hi>Obscure Darkness,</hi> even, into <hi>Utter Darkness:</hi> God has Reserv'd for you the <hi>Blackness of Darkness</hi> for ever. The very <hi>Children of the Kingdom</hi> themselves, have been cast into that hideous <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> when they have prov'd <hi>Undutiful.</hi> Be it known to you; That <hi>Undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> to your <hi>Parents,</hi> will bring you to <hi>feel many Stripes,</hi> from an Enrag'd <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> in the World to come; for you <hi>know the Will of God;</hi> Your <hi>Undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> is a Sin against your <hi>Conscience.</hi> Yea, be <hi>Dutiful</hi> to thy <hi>Parents,</hi> or expect all the formidable, outpourings of an Infinite and Eternal <hi>Wrath</hi> upon thy Soul. Thou dost not value the <hi>Wrath</hi> of thy <hi>Parents;</hi> It is a <hi>Light Thing</hi> to thee: But the <hi>Wrath of the Lord God Omnipotent,</hi> Oh, Don't make Light of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104904:28"/>
                  <hi>That; It is a fearful thing to fall into the Hands of the Living God!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope, we have been long enough upon Mount <hi>Ebal.</hi> Shall we now turn a little unto Mount <hi>Gerizzim?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Let the Signal <hi>Blessings</hi> of God, upon <hi>Children</hi> who treat their <hi>Parents</hi> with due <hi>Respect,</hi> find much <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect</hi> with you, be a great <hi>Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> unto you, have a strong <hi>Impression</hi> upon you. The <hi>Levites,</hi> as far as we understand, were to turn unto Mount <hi>Gerizzim,</hi> and with a loud voice to say, <hi>Blessed be he, who doth not set Light by his Father, or his Mother:</hi> And <hi>all the people</hi> were to say, <hi>Amen.</hi> Hearken, O my Children, to the <hi>Blessings</hi> of God, that shall be poured and showred from on High upon the <hi>Dutiful;</hi> and let them charm you, into all possible <hi>Dutifulness.</hi> there are <hi>Children,</hi> whose continual Desire and Prayer it is, That they may be in all Things made Rich <hi>Blessings</hi> unto their <hi>Parents.</hi> They <hi>Honour</hi> their <hi>Parents,</hi> and are an <hi>Honour</hi> to their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi> Their <hi>Parents</hi> do with <hi>Glad Hearts</hi> behold their <hi>Wisdom,</hi> and must bear this Testimony for them, <hi>Never
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104904:28"/>were Parents more Happy in their Children.</hi> O the <hi>Blessings</hi> that belong to <hi>Children</hi> of such a <hi>Character!</hi> If it might be said, as it was by <hi>David,</hi> when God gave him a Dutiful Son, that was to Build the <hi>Temple</hi> of the Lord; in Psal. 127.5. <hi>Blessed is the man, that hath his Quiver full of such Arrows,;</hi> Then surely, <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed are the Arrows, that are in the Quiver of such a man!</hi> The Holy Spirit of God sets a special Remark, upon that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which requires <hi>Children</hi> to be Dutiful unto their <hi>Parents:</hi> in Eph. 6.2. <hi>'Tis the First Command</hi> [of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table] <hi>with a promise, That it may be well with thee.</hi> It shall be <hi>well</hi> with you, O ye Dutiful Children: you have the word of a <hi>God</hi> for it. You may note it, That in the Command, what we Translate, <hi>That thy Days may be Long,</hi> is to be read, <hi>That they may prolong thy Days.</hi> Who are those <hi>They? They</hi> are thy <hi>Father,</hi> and thy <hi>Mother.</hi> But how can thy <hi>Father,</hi> and thy <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, prolong thy Dayes?</hi> How, but by <hi>Blessing</hi> of thee, in the Name of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. If the <hi>Dayes</hi> of such a Child be not <hi>prolong'd,</hi> we must allow a <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> in such Dispensations of Heaven; but there is cause to hope, for such a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104904:29"/>Child, that God has <hi>prolong'd</hi> his <hi>Dayes,</hi> in the Happiness of the Heavenly Word. This is plain; Those <hi>Parents,</hi> that are Blessed with Dutiful <hi>Children,</hi> do with an inexpressible Agony wish all sorts of <hi>Blessings</hi> to their <hi>Children.</hi> If it were in their power, to confer <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings</hi> upon their Children; Oh, how much would they do for them! Now because, 'tis in the power of God alone to confer <hi>Blessings</hi> upon us, these Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents go to God, for their Children, and they say with good old <hi>Jacob, God bless the Lads!</hi> I assure you, such Benedictions from <hi>obliged Parents,</hi> have a more than ordinary Authority, and Efficacy in them. For ones <hi>Parents</hi> to go before God, and plead, <hi>Ah, Lord, such a Child of mine, has Loved me, and Served me, and Helped me; and his good Carriage to me, has been such, that even upon that Account I have reason to wish him all the good in the world: I therefore bring that Child unto thee, and I pray thee to Bless him with all the Blessings of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness:</hi> To be thus <hi>Blessed</hi> by ones <hi>Parents,</hi> O my <hi>Children,</hi> 'tis a thing of more value than if a rich <hi>Inheritance</hi> were to be received from them. This is very
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104904:29"/>certain, There is no point of Religion, more certainly and commonly Rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>Blessings</hi> in <hi>this world,</hi> than that of rendring unto <hi>Parents</hi> the Dues that pertain unto them. A signal Pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, even in <hi>this world,</hi> uses to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend those <hi>Children,</hi> that are very Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient or Serviceable unto their <hi>Parents.</hi> Those <hi>Reckabites,</hi> that <hi>Obey the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Father, Thus said the Lord of Hosts, They shall stand before me for ever.</hi> There are <hi>Children,</hi> who have with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable pleasure, supported their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Parents,</hi> in their Necessities; They have said unto their Necessitous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, like <hi>Joseph, Thus saith thy Son, come down to me, Thou shalt be near to me:</hi> I believe, There are some at this very Time, in this very place, who can say, <hi>That from the Time, they did for their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents as they have done, God hath signally Smiled upon them.</hi> Friend, That Aged <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother,</hi> in thy House, is not only the Glory of thy House, but a better and a richer Thing than a Mine of Silver there.</p>
               <p>Children, Be <hi>Blessings</hi> to your <hi>Parents,</hi> and be Assured, That those <hi>Parents</hi> will be Greater <hi>Blessings</hi> to you, than you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104904:30"/>can be to <hi>Them.</hi> They will be so as Long as they Live; yea, more than so; After your <hi>Parents</hi> are Dead and Gone, the Effects of their <hi>Prayers</hi> will yet Live: All the Prayers which those Gratified <hi>Parents</hi> put up for you, will be still Answering, after they are Dead, as long as you your selves do Live. <hi>David</hi> had been a Son, very Tender of his <hi>Parents:</hi> and now, says, <hi>David,</hi> in Psal. 27.10. <hi>When my Father and my Mother forsake me, then the Lord will take me up:</hi> He'l Requite all that I did for my <hi>Father,</hi> and my <hi>Mother.</hi> Shall I go a step further? When you your selves also are Dead and Gone, even <hi>Your Children</hi> may Reap the Fruits of what you did for <hi>your Parents:</hi> Your <hi>Posterity,</hi> may fare the better for your <hi>Dutifulness.</hi> The Jews have a Notion among them; <q rend="margQuotes">That for the sake of the Honour, that <hi>Esau</hi> paid unto his Father, the <hi>Israelites</hi> Long after might not Extirpate the <hi>Edomites,</hi> who were the <hi>Posterity</hi> of <hi>Esau. Moses</hi> tells the <hi>Israelites, You have compassed this Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Long Enough.</hi> Why? Because <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sau</hi> compassed a <hi>Mountain</hi> in Hunting for his Father.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104904:30"/>
               <p>But after all; Dutiful <hi>Children</hi> acting upon principles of Christianity, may hope to meet with their Christian <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> in Heaven; There <hi>Abraham</hi> the Religious Father, There <hi>Isaac</hi> the Duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Son, There <hi>Jacob</hi> the Dutiful Grand-Son, are Together; Blessed are they that meet there, in the <hi>Light of the face of God;</hi> Blessed throughout Eternal Ages! Consider This, O Children; and <hi>Set not Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But being, by these Considerations prepared for it, it may now be Time to say;</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>III.</hi> The <hi>Respects</hi> that <hi>Children</hi> must render unto their <hi>Parents,</hi> are compriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in those <hi>Three Words, <hi>Reverence,</hi>
                  </hi> and, <hi>Obedieuce,</hi> and <hi>
                     <hi>Recompence.</hi> Children</hi> do <hi>Set Light</hi> by their <hi>Parents,</hi> or cast <hi>Contempt</hi> on them, if they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold any of these Three <hi>Regards</hi> from them: and the <hi>Curse</hi> of God, will Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the <hi>Contempt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, You <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if you withold from them, the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> that is due unto them. The God of Nature hath placed a <hi>Distance,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Parents</hi> and their <hi>Children; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:104904:31"/>then <hi>Set Light</hi> by their <hi>Parents,</hi> when they Forget this Distance. There is first, an <hi>Inward Reverence,</hi> that <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> owe unto their <hi>Parents.</hi> It was Enjoyned in Lev. 19.3. <hi>Ye shall Fear, every man, his Mother, and his Father.</hi> Children, you <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if your minds are not Struck, with some awful Apprehension of their <hi>Superiority</hi> over you; if you don't see an awful <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in their <hi>Superiority;</hi> if you don't look upon them, as the very <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in their several Families. But this <hi>Reverence</hi> must have some <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Expression</hi> given of it. There is an <hi>Outward Reverence,</hi> that <hi>Children</hi> owe unto their <hi>Parents</hi> Hence 'tis said, in Mal. 1.6. <hi>If I be a Father, where is my Honour?</hi> Hence 'tis said, in Prov. 31.28. <hi>Her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Rise up, and call her Blessed.</hi> Their <hi>Speeches,</hi> both <hi>to</hi> their <hi>Parents,</hi> &amp; <hi>of</hi> their <hi>Parents,</hi> must be full of <hi>Reverence.</hi> When <hi>Children</hi> speak <hi>to</hi> their <hi>Parents,</hi> their Language must carry in it, some Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of their being such. Thus, in Gen. 31.35. <hi>She said unto her Father, my Lord.</hi> When <hi>Children</hi> speak <hi>of</hi> their <hi>Parents,</hi> they must show a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, that nothing Abusive be uttered.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:104904:31"/>Thus, in Psal. 127.5. The <hi>Children of Youth,</hi> seem to Defend their <hi>Father,</hi> from the <hi>Enemies in the Gate,</hi> or, False-Accusers. And their <hi>Actions</hi> towards their <hi>Parents</hi> must yet more Emphatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Speak</hi> the <hi>Reverence,</hi> which they would Retain for them. Thus in Gen. 48.12. <hi>Joseph bowed himself, with his Face to the Earth,</hi> before his <hi>Father.</hi> Thus in 1 King. 2.10. <hi>Solomon Rose up to meet his Mother, and bowed himself unto her, and She Sat on his Right Hand.</hi> Now, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, you <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if you Talk Sawcily and Clownishly unto them; if you Reproach them, Defame them, and Backbite them; if your Behaviour towards them have any malapert Impudence in it. Though your <hi>Parents</hi> may give you never so <hi>much Occasion</hi> of Complaint, it becomes you to make as <hi>Little Reflection</hi> upon it, as ever you can. Say Nothing, but what the Glory of God makes it Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for you to say. Though they should happen to do you any Injuries, you may not show those Resentments, that you have upon the Injuries of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Persons.</p>
               <p>Again,</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104904:32"/>
               <p>Secondly; You <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if you withold from them, the <hi>Obedience</hi> that is due unto them. If <hi>Children</hi> don't Study to Do, what their <hi>Parents</hi> would have them to do; and if the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> of their <hi>Parents</hi> have not the Force of a <hi>Law</hi> upon them, the <hi>Children</hi> do <hi>Set Light</hi> by them, in such a misbehaviour. It was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Eph. 6.1. <hi>Children, Obey your Parents in the Lord, for this is Right</hi> Children, you <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if you don't count it a Right, a Just, a Fair Thing, and a Thing very Reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, for you to be the <hi>Servants</hi> of them, who have done so much for you their <hi>Children,</hi> and beware of <hi>Crossing</hi> them, who have done so much to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> you. It was said, in Col. 3.20. <hi>Children, Obey your Parents in all Things, for this is well-pleasing unto the Lord.</hi> But, <hi>Children,</hi> You <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if it be not also very <hi>Well-pleasing</hi> unto <hi>You,</hi> to <hi>Please</hi> them, so far as without Sin you may do it; and if you be not unwilling at any Time, to give them any Displeasure. When the Father of <hi>Joseph</hi> laid his <hi>commands</hi> upon him, he
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:104904:32"/>Obey'd those commands, though with the <hi>Risque</hi> of his very Life. It should be the very <hi>Joy</hi> of your Life, to yield <hi>Obedience</hi> unto the commands of your <hi>Parents.</hi> Do your <hi>Parents</hi> give you any <hi>Instruction?</hi> You are call'd upon, in Prov. 4.1. <hi>Hear, ye Children, the Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Father.</hi> Most of all, in the Grand <hi>Motions</hi> &amp; <hi>Changes</hi> of your Life, <hi>Children,</hi> your <hi>Parents</hi> are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted, and the Satisfaction of your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> is to be proposed. In your <hi>Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and in your <hi>Matches</hi> especially, the Directions of your <hi>Parents</hi> must be of Exceeding Moment with you; Indeed Nothing should be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them! Wherefore, <hi>Children,</hi> you <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if you make nothing of their <hi>Commands,</hi> and if you tread their just <hi>Reproofs</hi> under foot. You <hi>Set Light</hi> by them, if you <hi>Leave Undone</hi> what they <hi>Desire,</hi> and much more, if you <hi>Do</hi> what they <hi>Forbid.</hi> You <hi>Set Light</hi> by them, if their <hi>Anger,</hi> be a <hi>Light matter</hi> with you.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. You <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> if you withold from them the <hi>Recompence</hi> that is due unto them.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:104904:33"/>Those <hi>Children</hi> Evidently <hi>Set Light</hi> by their <hi>Parents,</hi> who are Insensible of the Obligations which their <hi>Parents</hi> have laid upon them, or, who count any thing too much to be done by <hi>Children</hi> for their <hi>Parents.</hi> Of <hi>Joseph</hi> 'tis said, in Gen. 47.12. <hi>He Nourished his Father, &amp; all his Fathers Houshold with Bread.</hi> And it is elsewhere pressed upon us, <hi>Despise not thy Mother, when she is old.</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, you <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents,</hi> if you don't <hi>Requite</hi> them as well as you can, and if you imagine that you ever can <hi>Requite</hi> them Enough. It was a Sad saying of <hi>Luthers,</hi> That <hi>One Father will more willingly maintain Ten Sons, than Ten Sons will maintain One Father.</hi> But those <hi>Children</hi> do <hi>Set Light</hi> by their <hi>Parents,</hi> who had not as liev maintain their <hi>Father,</hi> as maintain their <hi>Children;</hi> and who would not gladly be to their <hi>Mother,</hi> the <hi>Restorer of her Life,</hi> and the <hi>Nourisher of her old Age,</hi> as the Mother of <hi>Ruth,</hi> sound her <hi>Son-in Law</hi> to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her. It was demanded, in 1 Tim. 5.4. <hi>Let the Children Learn to show piety at home, and Requite their Parents; for that is Good and Acceptable before God.</hi> Those <hi>Children</hi> have no <hi>Piety</hi> in them,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104904:33"/>they <hi>Set Light</hi> by God, as well a by their <hi>Parents,</hi> unto whom it is not a most <hi>Acceptable Thing</hi> to make some <hi>Recompence</hi> unto their <hi>Parents,</hi> for all the vast Benefits which their <hi>Parents</hi> have heaped upon them. <hi>Children,</hi> Do you think, you can ever make a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence</hi> unto them, that have Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n you, and Bred you, and Fed you, and Endured Thousands of Sorrows for you. One says, <q rend="margQuotes">Many treat their <hi>Parents,</hi> as they do their <hi>Candles;</hi> they Set them in High <hi>Candle sticks,</hi> while they are full of Tallow, but when all their Substance is wasted, they tread them under foot.</q> And some there are, who do not <hi>Support</hi> their <hi>Parents,</hi> but <hi>Wrong</hi> them, and <hi>Rob</hi> them, and <hi>Pillage</hi> them; They <hi>Wast their Parents.</hi> Alas, Children, you <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Parents</hi> in all of this <hi>Impiety.</hi> But Oh, don't <hi>make Light</hi> of this <hi>Impiety;</hi> Say, <hi>Destruction from God is a Terror to me!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>IV.</hi> By <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother, <hi>all sorts of Parents</hi> are intended;</hi> Let the <hi>Caution</hi> be accordingly Extended, and <hi>Set Light</hi> by no sorts of <hi>Parents</hi> whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. <hi>Natural Parents</hi> cannot safely
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104904:34"/>come under the <hi>Contempt</hi> of their <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> God will <hi>Curse</hi> the <hi>Children</hi> that <hi>Set Light</hi> by <hi>Them;</hi> and can you dream then, that God will allow any <hi>Contempt</hi> of <hi>Political</hi> Parents, of <hi>Ecclesiastical,</hi> or of <hi>Scholastical?</hi> There are <hi>Parents</hi> in the <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Family;</hi> There are <hi>Parents</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Parents</hi> in the <hi>School,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi> If you <hi>Set Light</hi> by these <hi>Parents,</hi> you Herd your selves among the <hi>Cursed</hi> of God. Remember, O <hi>Servants,</hi> thy <hi>Master,</hi> is thy <hi>Father,</hi> and thy <hi>Mistress,</hi> is thy <hi>Mother.</hi> Do not <hi>Set Light</hi> by thy <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> or thy <hi>Mistress,</hi> Lest the <hi>Curse</hi> of God at last hang thee up in Chains, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Monuments of His Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Because thy <hi>Superiours</hi> in the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> are thy <hi>Parents,</hi> therefore there is laid that Charge of God upon thee, in 1 Pet. 2.18. <hi>Servants, be subject unto your Masters, with all Fear, not only to the Good &amp; Gentle, but also to the Froward.</hi> The Proud hearts of many <hi>Servants,</hi> make them discontent at their Servile State; The <hi>Subjection</hi> expected from them throws them into a very Grumbling Discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Ye proud Wretches, your <hi>Sin,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:104904:34"/>was the very Sin that at first made all the <hi>Devils</hi> in Hell. The <hi>Devils,</hi> those proud Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits could not bear to be <hi>Servants</hi> in such a Station as God had ordered for them; and for this their <hi>Pride,</hi> the Almighty has <hi>Cursed</hi> them, and <hi>Damned</hi> them. <hi>Servants,</hi> Have a care, Lest by your <hi>Pride</hi> you <hi>fall into the Condemnation of the Devil.</hi> It is the Providence and the Ordinance of the Lord Jesus Christ that hath made you <hi>Servants;</hi> and if out of Regard unto Him, you carry it well in your <hi>Servitude,</hi> He will graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously Accept all that you do, as if done unto Himself. It was therefore said, in Col. 3.23, 24. <hi>Servants, whatever ye do, do it heartily as unto the Lord, and not unto men; knowing that of the Lord you shall Receive the Reward of the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,</hi> [which belongs unto <hi>Sons:</hi>] <hi>for ye Serve the Lord Christ.</hi> Well then; Don't <hi>Set Light</hi> by your <hi>Masters. If they be Masters, where is your Fear of them?</hi> Expose not their <hi>Failings,</hi> if you see any in them. Let there be no <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenness,</hi> no <hi>Sawciness,</hi> no Rude Retort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in your Deportments towards them. Give them not cause to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, with <hi>Job, I called my Servant,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:104904:35"/>and he gave me no Answer.</hi> Be not those <hi>Eye-Servants,</hi> that will do their <hi>Masters Will,</hi> no longer then their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Eye</hi> is upon them; The <hi>All-seeing Eye</hi> of the Almighty <hi>God</hi> is upon you. Transgress not their just Commands, either <hi>wilfully,</hi> or <hi>Carelesly;</hi> If you do, the Commands of <hi>God</hi> are also <hi>Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed</hi> in your Miscarriages. Indeed, if your <hi>Masters</hi> bid you do an <hi>Ill Thing,</hi> you must with modest Expostulations, rather <hi>Suffer</hi> than <hi>Obey.</hi> But if they bid you do what is <hi>Fit</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> you Sin against <hi>God,</hi> if you do it not; If they will not obey you, <hi>Masters,</hi> Turn them out of Doors. Nor is this all that <hi>Servants</hi> have to do: <hi>Servants,</hi> you must use all <hi>Diligence,</hi> and <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness,</hi> in your <hi>Masters Business.</hi> A <hi>Slothful Servant</hi> is truly called a <hi>Wicked Servant.</hi> But <hi>Eliezer,</hi> the Servant of <hi>Abraham,</hi> would not Eat his Victuals, till his <hi>Masters Business</hi> were dispatched. Let your <hi>Masters Business</hi> be honestly discharged, though you should like <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> when a <hi>Servant,</hi> have your <hi>Sleep departing from your Eyes.</hi> When your <hi>Masters</hi> do send you, on <hi>Errands,</hi> Loiter not; Be not <hi>Sluggards to them that send
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104904:35"/>you.</hi> And be the true <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Israel;</hi> able to say, <hi>Thy Servants are True men. Gehazi</hi> was a <hi>Servant</hi> that <hi>Lyed</hi> unto his <hi>Master;</hi> but God made that <hi>Lyar</hi> to become a <hi>Leper.</hi> Of all Faults in your <hi>Servants,</hi> I advise you, <hi>Masters,</hi> never to let that of <hi>Lying</hi> be unpunished. But that of <hi>Stealing</hi> often accompanies it; of which, O <hi>Servants,</hi> beware; for God will never let <hi>That</hi> go unpunished. I vehemently call upon you, That you never venture to wrong your <hi>Masters</hi> unto the value of a <hi>Penny</hi> as long as you Live. Mark it, you'l Entail Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Vexations upon you, and God will make you loose a <hi>Pound</hi> for every <hi>penny,</hi> whereof you have <hi>wrong'd</hi> your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</hi> Have you ever <hi>purloined</hi> from them? Oh, Fly penitently unto the Blood of the Lord Jesus Christ for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and make as much <hi>Restitution,</hi> and as full <hi>Reparation,</hi> as ever thou canst; or the Jealous God, will never pardon thee, till the <hi>Torments</hi> of the Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have Exacted the <hi>utmost Farthing</hi> from thee. <hi>Servant,</hi> Be such a <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> in thy <hi>Masters</hi> House, as <hi>Joseph</hi> was to <hi>his.</hi> Contrive all the ways i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable, that thy <hi>Master</hi> may be
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104904:36"/>the better for thee. It may be, thy <hi>Master</hi> will <hi>Bless</hi> God for Thee. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>God</hi> will <hi>Bless thee</hi> in thy Serv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him. If you slight all these Things, Look for the <hi>Curses</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>And now, Let <hi>people</hi> Remember, That <hi>Rulers</hi> are <hi>Parents.</hi> Don't <hi>Set Light</hi> by <hi>Them.</hi> The Charge of God upon <hi>people,</hi> is That in Tit. 3.1. <hi>Be Subject, and Obey Magistrates, and be ready to every Good Work, and speak evil of no man;</hi> much less of the <hi>Magistrates.</hi> Our <hi>Setting Light by</hi> Excellent <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates,</hi> has been the Scandalous Crime of our Country; and for that Crime whole <hi>Colonies</hi> may come to smart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Revenges</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>Let <hi>Churches</hi> Remember, That <hi>Pastors</hi> are <hi>Parents.</hi> Don't <hi>Set Light</hi> by <hi>Them.</hi> The Charge of God upon <hi>Churches,</hi> is That in Heb. 13.17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and submit your selves; for they watch for your Souls, as they that must give Account, that they may do it with Joy, and not with Grief; for that is unprofitable for you.</hi> There hath been a Disorder, called, <hi>Corahism,</hi> sometimes very Extravagant. But for <hi>Setting Light</hi> by Ministers, that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:104904:36"/>have been Holy, and Able, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and Painful <hi>Men of God,</hi> God some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times removes a <hi>Candlestick out of its place,</hi> or at least says, <hi>Never shall a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and a Shining Light more be seen standing in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let <hi>Scholars</hi> regard their <hi>Tutors</hi> as their <hi>Parents.</hi> My Child, The <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> of the <hi>School</hi> is a <hi>Father</hi> to thee. Those that were under the Education of <hi>Moses,</hi> are called, <hi>The Sons of Moses</hi> Wherefore, <hi>Scholars,</hi> Do you with all Conscience of God, Honour your <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors;</hi> and perform the Tasks which they Impose upon you. Don't <hi>Set Light</hi> by thy <hi>School-Master;</hi> but Love him, and Prize him, and Hearken to him, and be Thankful to him, and Thankful to God for him. These are ways to Escape the <hi>Curses</hi> of God.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>V.</hi> They that have at at any Time <hi>Set Light</hi> by their <hi>Parents,</hi> must Go to God in Christ for His <hi>Pardons,</hi> that so His <hi>Curses</hi> may not overtake them. Who is there that can say with the Son in the Gospel; who <hi>said unto his Father, Lo, these many years do I Serve thee, neither Transgressed I at any Time
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104904:37"/>thy Commandment?</hi> The <hi>Dutifullest Child</hi> among us all, hath been so Defective in his <hi>Dutifulness,</hi> that he dare not plead it before God, in his <hi>Justification;</hi> He must say, as in Psal. 143.2. <hi>Lord, Enter not into Judgment with thy Servant; for in thy sight shall no man Living be Justified.</hi> What then shall we do? Why, we read concerning Mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> where the <hi>Curses</hi> of God were Fulmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated; in Deut 27.5, 6, 7. It was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>In Mount Ebal, thou shalt Build an Altar unto the Lord thy God, and thou shalt offer Burnt Offerings thereon unto the Lord thy God, and thou shalt Offer Peace-Offerings, and Rejoyce before the Lord thy God.</hi> And we find that <hi>Joshua,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards did accordingly. It is an Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Note of one upon it; <hi>This was no more than Needed, for the Maledictions had no sooner been uttered, but Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Execution had instantly Ensued, if these Sacrifices with the Merit of Christ therein Typified had not seasonably Interceded.</hi> Children, you hear the Convex of Heaven resounding from <hi>Ebal</hi> with the Comminations of God, <hi>Cursed is he that Sets Light by his Father or his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Our Consciences tell us, That we
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:104904:37"/>have done it many a time. Away then, Away to the Antitype of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> on <hi>Ebal.</hi> Oh, plead with God, the <hi>Burnt Offering</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Peace-Offering</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> that the <hi>Curse</hi> of God may not seize upon us, that we may not be <hi>Burnt</hi> in the Flames of His Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that He may be at <hi>Peace</hi> with us for ever. When it was denounced. <hi>Cursed is he that Sets Light by his Father or his Mother,</hi> it follow'd, that <hi>all the people said, Amen.</hi> AMEN, is the very Name of <hi>Christ.</hi> May <hi>all the people</hi> now fly to that, <hi>AMEN,</hi> that they may be sheltered from the <hi>Curses</hi> of God. And, Oh, call it to mind the <hi>Example</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ. There never was in the world, so Dutiful a <hi>Son</hi> as <hi>He!</hi> We read in Luk. 2.51. <hi>He went down with</hi> His <hi>Mother,</hi> and His Reputed <hi>Father,</hi> and though they were very Low, in the World, <hi>He became subject unto them.</hi> We read in Joh. 19.27. That when He was in his last Agonies, it was a Thing lying very near His Heart, that His <hi>Widow Mother,</hi> might be provided for: <hi>He said unto a Disciple, Behold, thy Mother!</hi> intimating that He would have him, <hi>take her Home unto his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104904:38"/>own House.</hi> Now, be your <hi>Dutifulness</hi> to your <hi>Parents,</hi> never so compleat, Let this <hi>Righteousness</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, be all that you will plead with God, as your Title to the <hi>promised Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings</hi> of the <hi>Dutiful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Do not Go on, <hi>Children,</hi> If you value your Lives, and Souls, do not Go on to <hi>Grieve</hi> your <hi>Parents,</hi> by any <hi>Disrespect</hi> unto their Admonitions, or by any <hi>Danity</hi> whatsoever. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not more <hi>Make Light</hi> of your <hi>Parents,</hi> than when you <hi>Make Light</hi> of <hi>their Counsels:</hi> your Contempt of <hi>their Counsels,</hi> will speedily bring down <hi>Gods Curses</hi> upon you. <hi>Moses</hi> did well, when he <hi>Hearkened unto the voice of his Father-in-law, and did all that he had said.</hi> It is the voice of Heaven, in Prov. 1.8. <hi>My Son, Hear the Instruction of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forsake not the Law of thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Is it not the <hi>Instruction of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> That thou shouldest avoid all <hi>Vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Company;</hi> and, That thou shouldest <hi>Pray in Secret</hi> every Day; and, That thou should Read and Hear the Word of God, with Assiduity? Or if not so, yet it may be, the <hi>Law of thy Mother,</hi> who is in Travailing pains for thee, to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:104904:38"/>see <hi>Christ formed</hi> in thee. Now, don't <hi>Make Light</hi> of the <hi>Admonitions,</hi> with which thy <hi>Parents</hi> are thus calling upon thee. If thy <hi>Parents</hi> Enjoin upon thee any thing that is not <hi>Sinful,</hi> it will be a <hi>Sin</hi> for thee to Refuse the doing of it: How much more is the <hi>Sin,</hi> if thou dost Refuse to do what the Great God has first Commanded, and thy <hi>Parents</hi> Enjoin because the Great God has first Commanded? Oh, my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, I am afraid, I am afraid, there are some of you, that may read your Doom, in those Ominous words, in 1 Sam. 2.25. <hi>They hearkened not unto the voice of their Father, because the Lord would slay them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is an unutterable <hi>Grief,</hi> that some of you give unto your pious <hi>Parents;</hi> They see, that you are still <hi>poor, carnal, and thoughtless</hi> Creatures: and that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a piece of gay Attire, is of more Account with you, than a <hi>Christ,</hi> or a <hi>Soul.</hi> 'Tis told them, That the <hi>Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Youths</hi> in the Town do horribly poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son one another. These <hi>Youths</hi> cry up an <hi>Indifferency in Religion,</hi> and say, <hi>'Tis out of fashion for a man to be of one Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion more than another;</hi> that is, in reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104904:39"/>to say, <hi>'Tis out of fashion to be of any Religion at all.</hi> So they insensibly draw one another on, to deride <hi>Seriousness</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> and the most Serious and Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preachers of it; Until they become Idle, profane, Sottish <hi>Debauchees,</hi> and betimes Ripe for the <hi>Fiery Indignation</hi> of God. Your <hi>Parents</hi> are Trembling, with an unknown Distress and Anguish, Lest you be Entangled in a <hi>Familiarity</hi> with these <hi>Ungodly Youths.</hi> It fills your <hi>Parents</hi> with a grievous Horror, That they cannot see the marks of a <hi>Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Soul</hi> upon you; They never hear you let fall a word, that may discover in you the least care of a Never dying <hi>Soul.</hi> They cannot find out, that there are any <hi>Transactions</hi> between the Lord Jesus and you, about the <hi>Salvation</hi> of a <hi>Soul</hi> in the Hands of the Destroyer. As <hi>Austin</hi> says, of his Blessed Mother, <hi>Toties Filios parturiebat, quoties a Deo eos deviare cernebat,</hi> so it may be said per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of thine, <hi>She never sees thee Sinning against God, but it brings the Anguish of a New Travail upon her.</hi> It may be, you once had some Good <hi>Beginnings,</hi> in <hi>Religion,;</hi> Your <hi>Parents</hi> felt their Hearts within them Leap for Joy,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104904:39"/>at those <hi>Beginnings;</hi> They Hoped, <hi>Well, This my Child was Lost, but is found, was Dead, but is alive!</hi> But seeing all your <hi>Goodness</hi> gone, like the <hi>Morning Cloud,</hi> and the <hi>Early Dew,</hi> it throws them into an Extream Consternation. How Cheerfully would they give all they have in the world, if they might say of you, <hi>Behold, they Pray!</hi> They are every Day Extreamly uneasy, least you Dy before you are <hi>New born,</hi> and it had been <hi>Good for you, that you never had been Born at all.</hi> Ah, <hi>Vain Children;</hi> Give, Give some Relief to this <hi>Grief</hi> of your <hi>Parents.</hi> Fall down before the Lord, and say, <hi>Lord, Thou shalt be my Father, and the Guide of my Youth.</hi> Turn to God in Christ, and become Devout <hi>Children; Then,</hi> say they, <hi>My Heart, O my Children, shall Rejoyce, even mine!</hi> But your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> count that you <hi>make Light</hi> of them, so long as you <hi>Lightly Esteem the Rock of your Salvation,</hi> and make Light of God, and Christ, and the Covenant of Grace. And now, I Earnestly testify unto you, That if you <hi>Go on,</hi> to Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God, and against your <hi>Parents,</hi> the <hi>Curses</hi> of the Great God are Impending over you: Those <hi>Curses</hi> will horribly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104904:40"/>
                  <hi>Wound the Head, of those that go on still in their Trespasses.</hi> Yea, though you are the Children of <hi>Pious Parents,</hi> the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> you might have had by <hi>that,</hi> shall be changed into a <hi>Misery.</hi> The more <hi>Pious Parents</hi> you have had, the more <hi>Forlorn Children</hi> shall you be throughout Eternal Ages. We read, that even the <hi>Children of Abraham</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, will be <hi>Cast into the Fire of the Wrath of God,</hi> if they do not bring forth <hi>Good Fruit</hi> before Him; And we read of such among the Damned, as Cry out, <hi>Oh! Father Abraham, I am Tormented in this Flame!</hi> It is a Strange passage, that I find lately published. The famous Dr. <hi>Twiss,</hi> had been a very wicked Boy: There Dyed a <hi>School fellow</hi> of his, that was more wicked than he: The Ghost of the Dead Lad, appeared unto <hi>Twiss,</hi> and horribly Cryed out, <hi>I am Damned!</hi> This was, as his worthy Son assures us, the occasion of <hi>Twiss</hi>'s Conversion unto God. Oh! Tis to be Feared, That many of our <hi>Young People,</hi> who have Dyed at home and abroad, and after the <hi>Madness</hi> of that <hi>Ungodly Life,</hi> by which they broke the Hearts of their <hi>Parents,</hi> are <hi>Gone unto the Dead;</hi> if they could in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:104904:40"/>Ghost now appear unto their <hi>Fellow-Sinners,</hi> yet Surviving, they would hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly Cry out, <hi>I am Damned! I am Damned, for my Ungodliness!</hi> But you have Enough to <hi>Warn</hi> you, against all Ungodliness, without <hi>One coming to you, from the Dead.</hi> And while we thus <hi>Warn</hi> you, there is this terrible Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be added unto all the rest. Refractory Child; Thy <hi>Pious Parents,</hi> themselves will not own thee, in the Day when God shall <hi>Curse</hi> thee, and cut thee off, and cast the out for ever. And all the <hi>Grief</hi> which thy <hi>Pious Parents</hi> here Endured for thee, and from thee, will but be Oyl to the Everlasting Flames of that Grief, which thou shalt Endure in the <hi>Place of Dragons.</hi> Oh, come to a <hi>Right Mind,</hi> Thou <hi>Prodigal;</hi> and by <hi>Repentance</hi> give unto thy <hi>Pious Parents</hi> cause to say, <hi>This is a dear Son, and a pleasant Child.</hi> Then the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Himself will <hi>Bless</hi> thee, and say, <hi>I will Surely have Mercy upon them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104904:41"/>
            <head>An Address, <hi>Ad Fratres in Eremo.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Syrs!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A Little Book to assist, <hi>The Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Children,</hi> is now in your Hands. But can they be well <hi>Educated,</hi> if their <hi>Parents</hi> never send them to SCHOOL? This is a point, that seems now to call for some Inculcation.</p>
            <p>A Good <hi>School</hi> deserves to be call'd, the very <hi>Salt</hi> of the Town, that hath it: And the <hi>Pastors</hi> of every Town, (who are, <hi>Sal Terrae,</hi>) are under peculiar obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, to make this a part of their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storal Care,</hi> That they may have a Good <hi>School,</hi> in their Neighbourhood. A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>putrefaction</hi> threatens the Rising <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> Barbarous <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable consequence of it, Outrageous <hi>Wickedness</hi> will make the Rising <hi>Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Loathsome, if it have not <hi>Schools</hi> to preserve it. But <hi>Schools,</hi> wherein the <hi>Youth</hi> may be able <hi>Masters</hi> be Taught the Things that are necessary to quality them for future <hi>Serviceableness,</hi> and have their <hi>Manners</hi> therewithal well formed under a Laudable <hi>Discipline,</hi> &amp; be over &amp; above <hi>Well Catechised</hi> in the principles of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> Those would be a <hi>Glory</hi> of our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104904:41"/>Land, &amp; the preservatives of all other <hi>Glory.</hi> The <hi>Minister,</hi> that shall give his Neighbours no Rest, until they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable <hi>Schools</hi> among them, and that shall himself also at some Times <hi>Inspect</hi> &amp; <hi>Visit the Schools,</hi> will therein do much towards Fulfilling that part of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, <hi>Feed my Lambs;</hi> &amp; his Neighbours under his Charge, will (whatever they think of it!) have cause to Bless God, for this Expression of his Faithfulness.</p>
            <p>But these are not the only persons, to whom <hi>this matter belongs;</hi> The Civil <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> &amp; the whole <hi>Vicinity,</hi> cannot be True to their own Interest, if they do not say, <hi>We also will be with thee.</hi> When the REFORMATION began, in <hi>Europe,</hi> an hundred and fourscore years ago, to Erect <hi>Schools</hi> every where, was one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal concern of the Glorious &amp; Heroic <hi>Reformers;</hi> &amp; it was a common thing even for Little Villages of Twenty or Thirty Families, in the midst of all their Charges, &amp; their Dangers, to maintain one of them. The <hi>Colonies</hi> of <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were planted on the Design of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing that Holy <hi>Reformation;</hi> &amp; now the <hi>Devil</hi> cannot give a greater Blow to the <hi>Reformation</hi> among us, than by causing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104904:42"/>
               <hi>Schools</hi> to Languish under Discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. If our <hi>General Courts,</hi> decline to contrive and provide <hi>Laws</hi> for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of <hi>Schools;</hi> or if particular <hi>Towns</hi> Employ their Wits, for Cheats to Elude the wholesome <hi>Laws;</hi> little do they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider how much they expose themselves to that Rebuke of God, <hi>Thou hast destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy self, O New England.</hi> Would we Read, in the ancient Histories, how zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous the more discreet <hi>Pagans</hi> were to maintain <hi>Schools</hi> among them; it might put us <hi>Christians</hi> to the Blush, among whom 'tis common for <hi>Schools</hi> to starve and sink; &amp; a mind sordidly covetous, <hi>Witholds more than is meet,</hi> but it tends unto what is Infinitely <hi>worse than poverty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Syrs, What will be the <hi>Issue</hi> of these Things? The <hi>Issue</hi> will be, That, <hi>Si Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia desideret pastorem, facilius Impostorem, inveniet quam pastorem; Et Res publica pro Doctore Juris, Juris Tortorem; Et pro me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis, mendici, pro praeceptoribus, Deceptores sese offerent.</hi> But least thro' the <hi>want</hi> of <hi>Schools,</hi> there should in a little while, be scarce one man in a place able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue this Description of the <hi>Fate</hi> so low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon that <hi>want,</hi> I will transcribe in plain <hi>English,</hi> the first Article of the, <hi>Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nostications
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104904:42"/>upon the Future State of</hi> New-England, lately published: <q rend="margQuotes">Where <hi>Schools</hi> are not vigorously and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably Encouraged, whole <hi>Colonies</hi> will sink apace, into a Degenerate &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Condition, &amp; at last become horribly <hi>Barbarous:</hi> And the first In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of their <hi>Barbarity</hi> will be, that they will be <hi>undone</hi> for want of men, but not see &amp; own what it was that <hi>undid</hi> them.</q> You will therefore pardon my <hi>Freedom</hi> with you, if I Address you, in the words of <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">If ever there be any Considerable Blow given to the Devils Kingdom, it must be, by Youth Excellently Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It is a serious Thing, a weighty Thing, and a thing that hath much of the Interest of Christ, and of Christianity in it, that Youth be well trained up, and that Schools, &amp; School-Masters be maintained. Learning is an unwelcome guest to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, &amp; therefore he would fain starve it out. But we shall never long retain the Gospel, without the help of Learning. And if we should have no Regard unto Religion, even the outward prosperity of a people, in this World, would necessarily require Schools &amp; Learned men. Alas, that none are carried with Alacrity &amp; Seriousness, to take care for the Education of Youth, and to Help the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104904:43"/>World with Eminent and Able men.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Freedom</hi> with which this Address is made unto you, is not so great as the <hi>Fervour</hi> that has animated it. My Fathers, and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, If you have any Love to God, &amp; Christ, &amp; Posterity; let <hi>Schools</hi> be more Encouraged. If you would not betray your Posterity into the very Circumstances of <hi>Salvages,</hi> let <hi>Schools</hi> have more Encouragement. But in the Anguish, the Despair, of Success to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise found by this Address, I will Turn it from you, unto the Almighty <hi>Hearer of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND, <hi>O thou Saviour, and Shepherd of thy</hi> New-English Israel: <hi>Be Entreated Mercifully to look down upon thy Flocks in the Wilderness. Oh, give us not up to the Blindness and Madness of neglecting the Lambs in the Flocks. Inspire thy People, and all Orders of men among thy People, with a just care for the Education of Posterity Let Well-Ordered, and well-instructed, and Well-maintained Schools, be the Honour and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Land. Let Learning, and all the Helps and Means of it, be precious in our Esteem and by</hi> Learning, <hi>let the Interests of thy Gospel so prevail, that we may be made wise unto</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>Save us, O our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST; <hi>Save us from the Mischiefs and Scandals of a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Uncultivated Off-Spring; Let this be a Land of Light, until Thou, O Sun of Righteousness, d<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thy self arise unto the World with Healing in thy Wings.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.
<pb facs="tcp:104904:43"/>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>